<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The new disorders of love A gallant novel. Written by Richard Gibbs, of Norwich, philo. medici.</title>
            <author>Gibbs, Richard, fl. 1681-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 180 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832581</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832581</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2146:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The new disorders of love A gallant novel. Written by Richard Gibbs, of Norwich, philo. medici.</title>
                  <author>Gibbs, Richard, fl. 1681-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Bentley and S. Magnes, in Russel-street, in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With three preliminary advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Harvard University Library copy imperfect; pages stained and torn, with some loss of print; considerable print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Harvard University Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Two copies on reel.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:1"/>
            <p>THE NEW DISORDERS OF LOVE. A Gallant Novel.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>RICHARD GIBBS,</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Philo. Medici.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and S. <hi>Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:2"/>
            <head>To his Honoured Friend, <hi>RICHARD BERNEY,</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> Eſq; El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son to Sir <hi>THOMAS BERNEY,</hi> Knight and Baronet, of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NEver till I had the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was I ſenſible how uneaſie Ambition ſits upon Mankind. This has made me labour long under the Pride of
<pb facs="tcp:37055:3"/> preſenting ſomething to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage; and deſign'd it upon a Graver Subject than what now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores your Protection. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Politeneſs of your Learning, and that there is nothing in the whole Circle of Sciences, that has eſcap'd the juſtneſs and ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your Cenſure, I durſt not ſtand the Teſt of ſo nice and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal a Critick, in offering any Philoſophical Eſſay to your View. This made me change the Deſign of putting off ſome of my imperfect Tracts under the Glory and general Approbation of your Name, in the Common-wealth of Learning, into that of Contributing to your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. A Relaxation of the Mind from more ſerious Studies, is often
<pb facs="tcp:37055:3"/> neceſſary to the largeſt and moſt vigorous <hi>Genius</hi>'s; and I am ſure by furniſhing to your Recreation, I gratifie all that know you. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Sir, I fancy the fair Sex will juſtifie me in this Addreſs: and there is poſſibly a World of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of a Noble Gentleman's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, whoſe Hearts, if we conſulted, would tell us, with how much Juſtice <hi>the Diſorders of Love</hi> lay Claim to his Protection. And here, Sir, an infinity of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preſents its ſelf for Panegyrick. And might I expatiate, I could run through a long Hiſtory of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of your Family; but that the World would tell me, that as the beſt of Families might pride themſelves in your Anceſtors, yet your own Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb facs="tcp:37055:4"/> are ſo tranſcendent, that the moſt illuſtrious of your Anceſtors, can pride themſelves in nothing more than you. And indeed, when the whole Nation was almoſt tainted, your Loyalty was Ermine-like. And thus you credited Arms, and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Good Mien. A Plain Dealer, Sir, would tax me here, I am ſure, with being wanting in your juſt Eulogies; but I am ſure I ſhall never be wanting in the Zeal, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and Paſſion, wherewith I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient, And moſt Humble Servant, <hi>RICH. GIBBS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:4"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Catalogue of ſome <hi>Novels</hi> and <hi>Plays</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <head>NOVELS.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>ZElinda,</hi> a fam'd <hi>Romance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Happy Slave,</hi> in three Parts.</item>
                  <item>3 Count <hi>Brion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 Count <hi>Gabales.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Hatige,</hi> or, the Amours of the King of <hi>Tamaran.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 Madam <hi>Lavalier,</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 Madam and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 Mad. <hi>Colonna</hi>'s Memoirs.</item>
                  <item>9 Queen of <hi>Majorca,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
                  <item>10 Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 Heroine Muſquetier.</item>
                  <item>12 Princeſs of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 Obliging Miſtreſs.</item>
                  <item>14 Fatal Prudence.</item>
                  <item>15 Princeſs of <hi>Fez.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16 Diſorders of Love.</item>
                  <item>17 Triumph of Love.</item>
                  <item>18 Victorious Lovers.</item>
                  <item>19 <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Almanzaida.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37055:5"/>
                  <item>20 Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>21 <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> or the Defender of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</item>
                  <item>22 <hi>Nicoſtratis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>23 Amorous Abbeſs.</item>
                  <item>24 <hi>Homais,</hi> Queen of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>25 Pilgrim, in two parts.</item>
                  <item>26 <hi>Meroveus,</hi> Prince of the Blood-Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>27 Life of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>28 Extravagant Poet.</item>
                  <item>29 <hi>Memoires Gallant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>30 Inſtructions for a young Nobleman.</item>
                  <item>31 Love-Letters from the <hi>Cavalier</hi> to the <hi>Nun.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>32 Gallant Ladies; or the Mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference: In two parts.</item>
                  <item>33 St. <hi>Lewis;</hi> or, the Politick Conduct of Queen <hi>Blanch.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>PLAYS.</head>
                  <item>1 <hi>Tartuff,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Puritan.</item>
                  <item>2 Forc'd Marriage, or the Jealous Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Engliſh Monſieur.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 All miſtaken, or the Mad Couple.</item>
                  <item>5 Generous Enemies, or the Ridiculous Lovers.</item>
                  <item>6 The Plain-Dealer.</item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Sertorius,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Nero,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Overthrow.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37055:5"/>
                  <item>10 <hi>Gloriana,</hi> or the Court of <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Mythridates,</hi> King of <hi>Pontus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 <hi>Oedipus,</hi> King of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14 <hi>Caeſar Borgia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>15 <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or the Force of Love.</item>
                  <item>16 Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> or the Witty Falſe One.</item>
                  <item>17 The Fond Husband, or the Plotting-Siſters.</item>
                  <item>18 Eſquire <hi>Old-Sap,</hi> or the Night-Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</item>
                  <item>19 Fool turn'd Critick.</item>
                  <item>20 Virtuous Wife, or Good Luck at Laſt.</item>
                  <item>21 The Fatal Wager.</item>
                  <item>22 <hi>Andromache.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>23 Country Wit.</item>
                  <item>24 <hi>Caliſto,</hi> or the Chaſte Nymph.</item>
                  <item>25 Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in two parts.</item>
                  <item>26 Ambitious Sateſman, or the Loyal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite.</item>
                  <item>27 Miſery of Civil War.</item>
                  <item>28 The Murder of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>29 <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                  <item>30 <hi>Hamlet,</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                  <item>31 The Orphan, or the Unhappy Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</item>
                  <item>32 The Soldiers Fortune.</item>
                  <item>33 <hi>Tamerlain</hi> the Great.</item>
                  <item>34 Mr. <hi>Limberham,</hi> or the Kind Keeper.</item>
                  <item>35 Miſtaken Husband.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37055:6"/>
                  <item>36 Notes of <hi>Morocco,</hi> by the Wits.</item>
                  <item>37 <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or the Unhappy Favourite.</item>
                  <item>38 Virtue Betray'd, or <hi>Anna Bullien.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>39 King <hi>Leare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>40 <hi>Abdellazor,</hi> or the <hi>Moor</hi>'s Revenge.</item>
                  <item>41 Town-Fop, or Sir <hi>Tim. Tawdery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>42 <hi>Rare en toui,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Comedy.</item>
                  <item>43 <hi>Moor</hi> of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>44 Country Wife.</item>
                  <item>45 City Politicks.</item>
                  <item>46 Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>47 Rehearſal.</item>
                  <item>48 King, and no King.</item>
                  <item>49 <hi>Philaſter,</hi> or Love lies a Bleeding.</item>
                  <item>50 Maids Tragedy.</item>
                  <item>51 Grateful Servant.</item>
                  <item>52 Strange Diſcovery.</item>
                  <item>53 Atheiſt, or the Second Part of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Fortune.</item>
                  <item>54 Wit without Money.</item>
                  <item>55 Little Thief.</item>
                  <item>56 Valiant <hi>Scot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>57 <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>58 <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>59 Amorous Prince.</item>
                  <item>60 <hi>Dutch</hi> Lovers.</item>
                  <item>61 Woman Bully.</item>
                  <item>62 Reformation.</item>
                  <item>63 <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>64 Love Tricks.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37055:6"/>
                  <item>65 <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>66 Fatal Jealouſie.</item>
                  <item>67 Mounſieur <hi>Ragou.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>68 Iſland Queen, or <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>69 Empreſs of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>70 Common-Wealth of Women.</item>
                  <item>71 The Noble Stranger.</item>
                  <item>72 Duke of <hi>Millain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>73 The Knave in Grain.</item>
                  <item>74 Amends for Ladies.</item>
                  <item>75 <hi>Manamochy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>76 The Emperor of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>77 The Wedding.</item>
                  <item>78 St. <hi>Patrick</hi> for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>79 <hi>Albumazor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>80 The Tragedy of <hi>Albertus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Some Books Printed and Sold by <hi>R. Bent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>BEaumont</hi> and <hi>Fletcher's</hi> Plays: in all, 51. in large Fol.</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Shakeſpear</hi>'s Plays: in one large Fol. Volume. Containing 43. Plays.</item>
                  <item>Biſhop <hi>Brownrig</hi>'s Sermons in Fol.</item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s Companion to the <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Altar:</hi> In Fol.</item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Aliſtry</hi>'s 40. Sermons: In Fol.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37055:7"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Towerſon</hi> on the Creed: in Fol.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hudebras</hi> Compleat: In 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Preſent State of <hi>England:</hi> In 2 Vol. in 12<hi>ves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Enter into the Cloſet: in 12<hi>ves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Evelin</hi>'s Calendarium Hortenſ. in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Rules of Civility: In 12<hi>ves.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mauger</hi>'s <hi>French</hi>-Grammar: the Twelfth Edition: In 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>French</hi> Common-Prayer: In 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>French</hi> Pſalms: in 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>French</hi> Teſtament and Pſal. in 12.</item>
                  <item>Moral Eſſays, in 4 Vol in 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plato</hi>'s Apology of <hi>Socrates:</hi> in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Natural Hiſt. of the Paſſions: in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Idolatry: in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Hoſt-worſhip: in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi>'s Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Creſſey:</hi> in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Proſpect of Humane Miſery: in 12.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi>'s Vanity of Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Bp. <hi>Andrew</hi>'s Devotions: in 12.</item>
                  <item>— His Manual for the ſick: in 12.</item>
                  <item>Perſwaſives to the Communion. By the Author of <hi>Enter into thy Cloſet:</hi> in 12<hi>ves.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37055:7"/>
            <head>THE NEW DISORDERS OF LOVE. A Gallant Novel.</head>
            <p>TWO Perſons of Quality in <hi>Picardy,</hi> being at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance about ſome Lands, plung'd themſelves over head and ears in Law; and for a long while perſecuted one another. They were near Relations, and of the ſame Family; both bearing the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37055:8"/> ſame Name, and the ſame Arms. Their Diſpute was about the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of an Eſtate, and of ſuch great Conſequence, as tended to one or the other's ruin. As they were eminent in their Province, their mutual friends made it their buſineſs to procure a Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for that purpoſe propos'd a Match. They had no more Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren than one Son and one Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and theſe friends having made them underſtand, that the means of removing all their differences, was to marry them together, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly reſolved ſo to do. The Son was not unhandſome, but whymſical in his humour: and as the advantages of the mind are to be preferr'd to thoſe of the body, he was not in the beſt Repute ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable in his Neighbourhood. The Daughter was agreeable, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed much. She was yet ſo green in years, as not to know the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Huſband. Thus when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37055:8"/> they talk'd of marrying her, ſhe ſeem'd indifferent; but when ſhe knew it to be to her Couſin, ſhe was extreamly afflicted. She told a woman that had had care of her Education, that better would it have been for her, that her Father had been caſt in his Law-ſuit. The woman made her anſwer, that ſhe wondered to hear her talk in that manner, and that there was nothing to be found fault with in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that was propoſed to her. As a Diſpenſation was neceſſary in this caſe, they ſent to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and while the Meſſenger was on his journey, the Marquiſs <hi>de Florange,</hi> ſo was her Suiter's Name, made love to her. He had lived almoſt altogether in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; inſomuch that his Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not wipe out the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageous Impreſſion ſhe had entertained of him. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the more ſhe ſaw him, the leſs ſhe eſteemed him; in him find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37055:9"/> many bad, and few good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
            <p>From that time ſhe did nought but weep, foreſeeing all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes wherewith ſhe was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. At laſt, the Diſpenſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, ſhe could not decline marrying him: but he enamoured her never the more after he was her Huſband, than he had done when he was her Gallant.</p>
            <p>In a little while after the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, a great Eſtate fell to <hi>Florange:</hi> and this enabled him to ſpend at an high rate. His Wife ſtudying to diſtance him, told him then, that we liv'd now in a Reign wherein Martial Men were only valued, and that though the bare thoughts of his abſence troubled her extreamly, yet could ſhe not but adviſe him to take upon him ſome Military Employ: That their Lands lying in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Forces, the means to preſerve them, was to do as Perſons of Quality did: That ſhe had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37055:9"/> heard, how that in the time of his Anceſtors a Soldier did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach 'em but with reſpect; and ſhould be overjoyed he might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain have the ſame influence.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs <hi>de Florange</hi> was of a Family that had produc'd brave men; but the Valour of his Anceſtors had not reach'd his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; inſomuch that he had been but one ſingle Campaign in the Army: Nay, and he returned thence two months before the reſt, as in no wiſe delighting in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Thus finding little ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in his Wives Diſcourſe, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, that her contrivance lay to get him out of the way; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Concerns of his Family, that wedded him to his own houſe, he was in no wiſe enclined to give her that ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs was picqu'd by his anſwer; and as this his carriage ſpoke his little regard for her, ſhe told him, that it was long ſince ſhe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37055:10"/> had begun to take notice of his ill humour; but that it was not fitting he ſhould cloak his Capriciouſneſs with a Pretext that did an injury to others. And ſhe happened to mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him out a Coward: and as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo offenſive as truth, the Marquiſs fell into an extraordinary rage; and they proceeded to give one another hard words.</p>
            <p>Some days after, <hi>Florange</hi> being obliged to go thence to <hi>Paris,</hi> upon a Proceſs of Conſequence, was at a plunge, whether he ſhould take his Wife along, or leave her at home. He began to be jealous of her, yet without cauſe; for as yet ſhe ſaw no body that either had a deſign upon her, or on whom ſhe could be accus'd of having any. But whether that <hi>Florange</hi> had a ſecret foreknowledg of his misfortune, or that really he in her found ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Gallantry, ordered one of his Domeſticks before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, to have an eye upon her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37055:10"/> actions. This Domeſtick was a middle-aged man, and ſeemed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcreet. He had been in the Wars in his Youth, where he had learnt to live; but this was all the profit he had made by them; for having been reform'd upon the <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaean</hi> Peace, and being deſtitute of maintenance, he was forced to accept of the firſt Employ that was propoſed to him; and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>de Florange</hi>'s Father having offered him his houſe, he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly liſted himſelf in his Family, as his Gentleman of the Horſe, and to have an eye upon his Son, who was then very young. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was mean for ſuch a man as he; but neceſſity made him paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all things. Yet though his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was low, his heart was not the leſs: and indeed he had never lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved other than women of Quality, and from the time he firſt ſaw the Marchioneſs, he found he was not proof againſt her Charms. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37055:11"/> Reſpect kept him ſilent. But the Marquiſs his Commiſſion begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſooth him, he fancied ſome Change might happen in his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and that he might inſinuate himſelf into the Marchioneſs's good Opinion, he imparted the Order to her he had received from her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; and aſſured her that he was more at her Devotion than at any bodies in the world. The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs was ſurprized at this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, yet not ſo much for the knowledg it gave her of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Jealouſie, as for this mans good will. For as he had been a long while with the Marqueſs <hi>de Florange,</hi> and his Father, ſhe could not apprehend how he ſo lightly quitted their Intereſts, to embrace thoſe of a perſon he but lately knew. After that this thought had poſſeſſed her for ſometime, inſtead of gueſſing at what thus byaſſed <hi>Grand Champ,</hi> ſo was the Name of this Domeſtck, ſhe imagined that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37055:11"/> he had perceiv'd her innocence, and had only offered her his ſervice out of compaſſion.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, if her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had not ſeemed over-amiable to her before this, ſhe then thought him altogether horrible, and at his return from <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhe had all the pain imaginable to endure him. He came back at length towards the end of Summer, which was very bad that year, by reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Rains. The ſucceeding <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn</hi> was ſtill more unpleaſant, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that all the People of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Countrey, ſeeing the bad weather, talk'd of repairing into the Cities. The greater part went to <hi>Paris;</hi> but the Marquis did not think it convenient to carry his Wife thither, he thinking her of too <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> an humour. He knew the Huſbands were not in ſafety there; eſpecially thoſe that are not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amiable, and have very lovely Wives. The Marchioneſs expected
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37055:12"/> to ſpend the Winter in that Town, he having promiſed ſhe ſhould in the beginning of the Summer; but ſeeing he changed his mind, this ſtill help'd to make her hate him the more. Nevertheleſs, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not over-much delight in a Countrey-houſe, he reſolv'd to go into ſome ſmall City, where the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence was not ſo maligne for mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried people as it might be at <hi>Paris.</hi> His Eſtate lay about <hi>Soiſſons;</hi> and this was the place he choſe in which to recreate himſelf during the bad wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This Town is ſo pretty, inſomuch that the Marchioneſs lov'd it how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever better than her Village. No ſooner were they got thither, but that the Kings Army in <hi>Flanders</hi> had Orders to ſeparate, and march a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to their Winter-Quarters. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Officers in their Road to <hi>Paris,</hi> paſſed through <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, of an extraordinary merit, and of a very eminent Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; his Regiment had encamped
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37055:12"/> the year a-fore near the Walls of the Town, with five or ſix others, that had ſtaid there for fifteen days, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he had ſpent that time in making his Court to a Citizen's Wife; and he came purpoſely to ſee her again, ſhe having not uſed him ſeverely.</p>
            <p>After he had ſeen her, knowing <hi>Florange</hi> to be at <hi>Soiſſons</hi> with his Lady, he paid him a Viſit. They had made acquaintance at <hi>Paris</hi> two years before, but had never ſeen the Marchioneſs, though he had heard her highly extolled. He found her Fame was ſtill ſhort of her Beauty and Merit, inſomuch that he could not forbear telling <hi>Florange</hi> what he thought of his Choice. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs; though of a temper to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily jealous, was not alarm'd at the praiſes he conferr'd upon his Wife, as knowing Courtiers to be prodigal of them.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs, on her ſide, liked the Colonel extreamly, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37055:13"/> was as much charm'd with his good Meen as his Reputation; for he had perform'd Actions in War that had made him very conſpicuous.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs <hi>de Florange</hi> asked him what brought him to <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> becauſe that was not the direct way to go to Court; and as young peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have commonly more Vanity than Diſcretion, the Marquiſs <hi>de Mainville,</hi> ſo was this Officer called, own'd ingenuouſly the love he had for the Citizen's Wife, and that ſhe was the cauſe of his little journey. After this ſecret, <hi>Florange</hi> did not wonder to ſee him ſtay ſome time in the City, and the more becauſe that people began already to talk of his Intrigue. As ſoon as the Rumour of it came to the Marchioneſſes ears, ſhe perceiv'd her ſelf vex'd at the Choice he had made, as if ſhe had already intereſſed her ſelf in him. She muſt needs ſee the Woman that had made ſo fine a Conqueſt; but ſhe ſaw her not, ſave with the Eyes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37055:13"/> of a Rival; for though ſhe was paſſably beautiful, ſhe found her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unworthy of the thoughts of a man of Honour. <hi>Mainville</hi> knew not what paſſed in his favour in the Marchioneſſes boſome; but without penetrating into her ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he had ſuch for her, as came very near thoſe ſhe had for him. He found her infinitely lovely, and her Huſband, on the contrary, ſeem'd to him unworthy of poſſeſſing her.</p>
            <p>He had been told, that he was the moſt jealous of all men, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he pitied her, being fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en into the hands of a Perſon, who ſo little knew how to reliſh the happineſs he had in poſſeſſing ſo beauteous a Woman. However, though this thought poſſeſſed him wholly, he endeavoured to conceal it as much as he could from all the World, for fear of creating Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Marqueſs <hi>de Florange</hi>'s Breaſt, who after that, would not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37055:14"/> fail of forbidding him to come to his houſe, or of carrying his Wife back into the Countrey. Thus he reſolved to uſe ſo much Myſtery in his Love, that no body ſhould have the leaſt inckling of it, ſave the Marchioneſs, bounding all his cares to tell her in private what ſhe had kindled in his heart. Thus he for nothing reckon'd the conſtraint he lived in, being well enough ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, provided he gave no jealouſie to her Huſband. He hoped hereby to render himſelf agreeable to the Marchioneſs, as knowing that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, above all things, prize Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. But the Sympathy they had entertained for one another at their firſt enterview, had already produc'd ſo much effect upon her, that there was no need of this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Civility, to inſinuate him into her good Opinion. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed whatever her Vertue could dictate to her, to ſtifle certain agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able motions ſhe was ſenſible of in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37055:14"/> her ſelf, upon thinking on him, ſhe could not overcome them. Thus ſhe perceiv'd, that if ſhe meant to preſerve her Innocence, ſhe muſt diſtance her ſelf from a place where ſhe could not ſtay, without running the riſque of being ruin'd. But much ado had ſhe to come to this Reſolution, becauſe nothing is ſo difficult to reject, as agreeable thoughts; but conſidering it to be the only means to ward off the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions with which ſhe was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhe deſired the Marquis <hi>de Florange,</hi> that he would go to his Countrey-houſe; if not, that he would ſuffer her to go thither with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him.</p>
            <p>He ask'd her, what could be the cauſe of ſo great a change; and her anſwer was, that the Air of the Town injur'd her, and that that of the Countrey would be much better for her. Yet as ſhe looked well, he thought this to be only a Pretext, and was not over-haſty to grant her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37055:15"/> her requeſt. Beſides, he himſelf hated, as I have ſaid, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, inſomuch, that for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oblig'd of returning thither, he deſir'd the Marquis <hi>de Mainville</hi> to prevail with her to ſpend the Winter at <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> telling him, that ſhe would ever contribute towards his Diverſion, in caſe he made any ſtay in that Town. <hi>Mainville,</hi> who had hitherto in vain waited for an occaſion to ſpeak to the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in private, was over joy'd at this which Fortune ſent him. He went at the ſame time into her Chamber, and ſurpriz'd her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly by his manner of coming thither; for he was quite out of countenance, and as a man newly labouring under ſome great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. She ask'd him, what put him upon coming to ſee her, he that had not been to ſee her ſince he came to Town: and this obliging reproach affording him matter of entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Diſcourſe, he made her anſwer,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37055:15"/> that it would be eaſie for him to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her upon that point, if ſhe would take the trouble of hearing him. Thereupon he acquainted her how paſſionately he had lov'd her from the firſt moment he ſaw her; but that having perceiv'd the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous humour of her Huſband, he had kept that ſtrict hand upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he believ'd neither he nor ſhe had taken notice of his Paſſion. That <hi>Florange</hi> ſent him thither to diſcourſe her upon buſineſs; but being unable to live any longer without knowing after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhe would receive the offers of his ſervice, he took that time to ask her, whether ſhe would render him unhappy, that he had blaz'd about his deſign to lye upon another; but that the perſon he had pretended to love, ſerv'd only for a Cover to his real inclinations, ſince he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of loving any other than her.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37055:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Diſcourſe ſeem'd to be extreamly grateful to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, ſince ſhe was as fervently lov'd by him as ſhe lov'd him; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſhe fell a weeping, as if he had inform'd her of the Death of all her Friends. So extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a procedure put <hi>Mainville</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an extraordinary ſurprize. He ask'd her, why ſhe griev'd ſo very much; but the more he preſſed her to anſwer him, the more her grief ſeemed to augment. He then fell to eying her from head to foot, fearing ſhe was not over-wiſe. This thought had been capable of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him; but the Marchioneſs breaking ſilence, told him, he would not wonder at her tears af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what ſhe had to acquaint him withal: That ſhe lov'd him as much at leaſt as he could love her; and that this her weakneſs made her fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: That her Deſign was to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her Vertue; but that it was difficult to anſwer for it, when one
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37055:16"/> had ſuch an inclination for a perſon, as ſhe had for him. She then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him of the requeſt ſhe had made to her Huſband, of carrying her back to their Countrey-houſe, that ſhe might have the means of ſhunning his ſight; and <hi>Mainville</hi> knew well enough that ſhe ſpoke the truth, ſince he himſelf was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd to divert her from her Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <p>As it is natural to flatter ones ſelf, <hi>Mainville,</hi> inſtead of being alarm'd at her Vertue, thought only to thank her for her kind thoughts of him; but the Marchioneſs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him in the midſt of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, told him roundly, that he was not yet got where he imagined, and that the more ſhe was ſenſible of her weakneſs, the more efforts ſhe was going to uſe never to ſee him again. It is eaſie to imagine, that he attempted to inſpire her with other Sentiments, and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his utmoſt Wit for that purpoſe;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37055:17"/> but the Marchioneſs was a Woman of Courage, inſomuch that after having left him, ſhe ſent for <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> to deſire a great ſervice of him. That he had great Credit in her Huſbands good Opinion, and wiſh'd he would employ it ſo, in obtaining his permiſſion for her to return into the Countrey. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was ſurpriſed at this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as knowing the averſion the Marchioneſs had for a ſolitary life. Thus his anſwer was, that ſhe thought not on what ſhe ſaid; and turning her Diſcourſe into Railery, he aſſured her he ſhould ever be ſo careful of her content, as not to procure her a thing as would ſo much accrue to her diſſatisfaction. Then was the Marchioneſs oblig'd to put on her moſt ſerious looks, to let him know that ſhe ſpoke in good earneſt; and at length ſhe did ſo thorowly repreſent to him, that it would be the doing her a kindneſs, that he promiſed her to do all he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37055:17"/> could with <hi>Florange,</hi> to content her in her deſires. The Marchioneſs in diſcourſing <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> was as free in her ſpeech with him, as ſhe might be with a man whoſe Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation could not be of any Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, inſomuch that ſhe chanc'd to ſay, that ſhe ſhould be as happy with him in a Village, as if ſhe was in the beſt City in the world. This man did not want a good Opinion of himſelf, inſomuch, that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting theſe words at the foot of the Letter, he thought he was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier than he had imagin'd. He had ever cloak'd his Love with the appearances of Civility and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; he then imagin'd, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being too vain, he might give it leſs narrow bounds. Thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd on the firſt occaſion, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan himſelf for the Sentiments he had ſo long entertained for her, not doubting but that the ſucceſs would be anſwerable to his hopes.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37055:18"/>
            <p>The Marchioneſs did from day to day wait for her Huſband's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, when <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> to cut off what was leaſt neceſſary, told her, that he found it difficult to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what ſhe deſired; but that he would not deſiſt however. In the ſpace between the Marchioneſſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s anſwer, she ſaw the Marquiſs <hi>de Mainville</hi> again; and his Viſits did not help to cure her of her Paſſion. On the contrary, she became ſo ſenſible, that she was afraid, that if theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews laſted any long time, she should have much a do at length to reject his perſecutions; for he was too urging. Wherefore she told <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> that she had a ſecret to truſt him withal, but that being of the utmoſt moment to her, to confide it only in the hands of a man, on whoſe diſcretion she might relie; she would have him firſt ſwear, that he would never ſpeak of it to any body. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37055:18"/> pre-poſſeſſed, as I have ſaid, with a great Opinion of himſelf; and this diſcourſe fully perſwading him of his good fortune, he made a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Oaths of Fidelity to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, to induce her to declare her ſecret to him. She thereupon told him, that though it was not handſome for a Lady to own her weakneſs, ſhe could not however conceal it any longer, without ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it remedileſs. That ſhe had an inconceivable confuſion for it; but that he ought rather to pity than blame her; and ſo much the more, as that ſhe uſed her utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, as that ſhe might have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to reproach her ſelf withal: That ſhe was going to unboſom to him, to the very ſecret motions of her heart, that it would be for him to condemn her after this, if he found her culpable.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Marchioneſs had ſaid nothing but what entertained <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> in his fooliſh hopes;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37055:19"/> but when ſhe had declar'd to him the Paſſion ſhe had for <hi>Mainville,</hi> and that he had for her, he was, for all the world, in as great confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as if he had been caught in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ill action. <hi>How Madam,</hi> cry'd he, after ſome moments of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>You love the Marquiſs</hi> de Mainville! <hi>the Marqueſs de</hi> Mainvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, <hi>who is over head and ears in love with a Citizen's Wife, and who out of Courtſhip to her, has abandon'd the Care of his Fortune? Yes, I love him,</hi> the Marchioneſs reply'd faintly, <hi>and my deſiring to diſtance my ſelf from hence, is only for that I am afraid of loving him too much. Many Women in my place, would perhaps contrive the means of ſeeing him on all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but for my part, I mean to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void him, becauſe he has a ſecret Charm, againſt which I cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my ſelf. Ah Madam! Grand-Champ</hi> reply'd, to whom all theſe words were as ſo many ſtabs into his heart; <hi>ſeek an other Confident
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37055:19"/> than me; I find not my ſelf proper to render you the ſervice you require of me, and I ſhould deceive you if I had promiſed you.</hi> At theſe words he went his way, all tranſported with anger, without vouchſafing to hear her farther. The Marchioneſs did what ſhe could to detain him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very willing to clear all his ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; but ſhe took her time ill, ſince the rage he was in to ſee himſelf fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from his hopes, put him into an inconceivable Deſpair.</p>
            <p>As he had manifeſted a great deal of Paſſion in the reproaches he had made her, it was no difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Marchioneſs to know, that he was <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Rival. She call'd to mind a world of actions that Love had made him commit, which ſhe had not minded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but which then confirm'd her in the thought ſhe had of him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that ſhe was extreamly vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſhe had made him her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. However, as there was now
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37055:20"/> no Remedy, ſhe fell to contriving how to appeaſe him, and fancied ſhe might do it, had he any reaſon left. For ſhe repreſented to her ſelf, that not being Miſtreſs of her own heart, he ought to be ſatisfied with the efforts ſhe made to ſtifle her Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and with the Reſolution ſhe had taken to withdraw into the Countrey. Said ſhe likewiſe to her ſelf, that if he lov'd her, he would help her to obtain her Huſband's leave for that purpoſe, which she paſſionately deſired, ſo to root out a Love, which all agreeable as it was, yet made her labour under great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions.</p>
            <p>While ſhe was expecting this from <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s jealouſie, <hi>Mainville</hi> being allarm'd at the inſtances ſhe made to <hi>Florange,</hi> that ſhe might leave the City, did ſlily inculcate ſuſpicions in the mind of that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Huſband; ſometimes telling him, after a drolling manner, that his Wife was in love with ſome or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37055:20"/> other in his Neighbourhood. But <hi>Florange,</hi> who far from being tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable upon that matter, was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of the leaſt thing, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch diſadvantageous impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of her Conduct, that when ſhe ſpoke to him again, of returning to their Countrey-houſe, he not only deny'd her, but did it after ſuch a diſobliging manner, that ſhe was netled to the very heart. At firſt ſhe had recourſe to her fears; but Grief having made room for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, it came into her head, to revenge her ſelf that way he moſt apprehended. For ſome time ſhe found a certain pleaſure in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her ſelf, with this thought; but her Vertue having got the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant, ſhe bluſht for having been capable of conceiving a thing to her ſo diſadvantageous.</p>
            <p>In a few days after, <hi>Grand Champ</hi> entred her Room with a wild, ſtaring look, and ſuch as ſuited very much with the ſtate of his Soul. He told
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37055:21"/> her, that he came to take his leave of her, and that he had at that time ſuch concerns upon his hands, as oblig'd him to be gone. His Complements ſurpris'd the Marchioneſs. She en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to divert him from his Reſolution, rightly gueſſing at the occaſion; but he made her anſwer, that he could not ſtay any longer in a place where he ſhould have dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before his Eyes, a Rack a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more cruel than Death it ſelf. That after what ſhe had told him, as he knew the effects of Love, he did not doubt but that the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe had for the Marquis <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> would rather augment than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh; that he foreſaw ſtrange Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, not that he ſuſpected her of being ever wanting to her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but out of the knowledge he had of her Huſband's jealous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, who would be over joy'd to find a Pretext to uſe her ill.</p>
            <p>Thus did <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> under fine appearances, conceal the real
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37055:21"/> Cauſe of his diſcontent: for it was only Jealouſie that induc'd him to deſire to be gone. In the mean while he put a thouſand fears into the Marchioneſſes head, by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes with which he threatned her: and if the love ſhe had for <hi>Mainville,</hi> had not already been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry violent, his Diſcourſe had been capable of clearing her heart of it intirely. She could have wiſh'd it had been in her power ſo to have done. And indeed that ſhe might have a perſon to ſuſtain her ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue, ſhe conjur'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> not to abandon her in her preſent Condition, promiſing him to do all things imaginable to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her weakneſs. <hi>You'l ſee,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>that the love I have for</hi> Mainville, <hi>is not an effect of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination; and that one's Star may be rectify'd, when it would hurry us into the precipice againſt our wills. And indeed to what uſe would our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be, if we cannot put it in practice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37055:22"/> when we have need of it? and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, what difference would there be between Men and Beaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was ſo troubled, that he could hardly underſtand one bare word of what the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs ſaid; but ſeeing ſhe preſs'd him a new to give her anſwer: <hi>What would ye have me tell you, Madam,</hi> he reply'd to her, <hi>and will you force me, willy nilly, to own my Crime t' ye? I am as culpable as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate; I know what I am, and what you are; and the knowledge I have of both, has not hindred me from loving you. I adore you, ſince I muſt needs tell you ſo, and you adore the Marquis</hi> de Mainville. <hi>After this, the only courſe for me, is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance my ſelf from hence; and tho you ſhould pardon me the exceſs of my temerity, I could not pardon my ſelf for it, and for having dar'd to love you, without being capable of exciting the ſame flames in you as you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in me. An other inſpires you
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37055:22"/> with thoſe agreeable movements, which I would make you ſenſible of at the coſt of my life. Thus it is no longer pleaſant to me, ſince I have nothing more to hope.</hi> At theſe words he would have gone his ways, without ſtaying for an anſwer; but the Marchioneſs re-calling him, made him turn his Head againſt his will; and he obſerv'd an inconceivable grief in her face. <hi>What would ye have of me, Madam,</hi> he then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, with an air wherein Love and Deſpair did equally appear? <hi>Would ye have me ſuffer here all that is moſt cruel for man to ſuffer? That I ſee every day before me the moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lady living, without daring to lift up my Eyes to her: Thus I contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the love I have for the Marquis</hi> de Mainville, <hi>and that inſenſible to the one or other, I lead out the moſt languiſhing life in the world: No, Madam, you ought not to oblige me to this: you your ſelf would be a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, in ſuffering ſuch a Wretch as I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37055:23"/> am, to dare to tell you, that he loves you; and though you could bear with it, yet it would not eaſe me; I ſhould have ever before my Eyes the Marquis</hi> de Mainville<hi>'s happineſs; and perhaps that believing my ſelf as worthy of being belov'd as he, notwithstanding the difference there is between our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, I ſhould tell you things as might diſpleaſe you. It is better for me all at once to diſtance my ſelf from the moſt amiable perſon breathing; and though it coſt me my Life, Death will be more pleaſant to me than a ſight that will make me die every moment.</hi> At theſe words he would again have been going, but the Marchioneſs holding him by the arm, told him, that if he was minded to oblige her, he would ſtill ſtay with her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: That ſhe bore him not ſo much ill will for his temerity, as ſhe might have done at an other time, becauſe ſhe her ſelf knew the power of Love. That as to the reſt, ſhe was willing to forget all things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37055:23"/> he promis'd her never to ſpeak to her of his Paſſion. That Reaſon muſt govern him, as she pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd him to let it govern her her ſelf: That she would have him to be a Witneſs of the efforts she was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make, to drive <hi>Mainville</hi> out of her heart; and that if she could not effect that, he would, at leaſt, be with her to mind her of her Vertue.</p>
            <p>In fine, as it is impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt what one loves, <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> could not decline obeying the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, and continued to ſtay with <hi>Florange.</hi> Nevertheleſs if she had ſo much indulgence for him, it was not without very powerful reaſons. She conſider'd, that the exceſs of his Diſpair might prompt him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal her ſecret, and that it would be better for her to conſtrain her ſelf, than be expos'd to the anger of a Lover, who had juſt occaſion to complain. On the other ſide, as her deſign was to be vertuous, she
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37055:24"/> imagin'd that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence would be capable of keeping her in, and that narrowly watching her actions, she should be asham'd after what ſhe had told him, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting any Weakneſs.</p>
            <p>Thus while she was ſtudying all poſſible means for her ſecurity, <hi>Mainville</hi> omitted nothing of what might give a happy ſucceſs to his Love. He from time to time found the means of diſcourſing the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs; and his Converſation ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd that Ladies Projects. She dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover'd ſome new Quality in him, as render'd the Vice leſs hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to her, inſomuch that she was no longer ſo very deſirous to return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Florange,</hi> all jealous as he was, perceiv'd nothing as yet; but the Citizen's Wife, whom <hi>Mainville</hi> had courted before, finding him more faint than ordinary, examin'd the Cauſe of it, and was not long without detecting it. Her Rage,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37055:24"/> upon this, was extream; and she was upon the point of letting her jealouſie break out, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering she should injure her ſelf as much as the Marchioneſs. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſtill fearing to be deceiv'd, she would have new Proofs of her Lover's Infidelity, before she pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to Reproaches againſt him, and to Invectives againſt her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</p>
            <p>This Citt, though not of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did nevertheleſs make ſome Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the Town, as being very rich, and paſſably handſome. She was one in all the Merry-meetings of that place; and the ſeaſon of the Carnival then requiring people to be in Diſguiſe, as is the Cuſtom, <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> deſir'd her to make one in a Maſquerade, which <hi>Mainville,</hi> and his Wife were to be of. And that they might be the finer, they ſent for Cloaths from <hi>Paris,</hi> ſix for Men, and ſix for Women. They were all alike, and ſuited well enough with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37055:25"/> an Entry. They meant to dance at the Wedding of a very pretty Maid, that was to be very ſuddenly marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. That Day being accordingly come, they procur'd the admiration of all the Company, who were not wont to ſee people that danc'd ſo well as did <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs <hi>de Florange.</hi> After they had danc'd, theſe Lovers plac'd themſelves by one another, and <hi>Mainville,</hi> on whom the Citt had her Eyes fixt, having careſs'd the Marchioneſs a little too much, it is difficult to expreſs her vexation on that account. Being tranſported with anger, she went inſtantly to make a thouſand Reproaches to that perfidious man; but having met in the way a female friend of hers, that ſtopp'd her, she neither found <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> nor the Marchioneſs, who had left their places to take others. She endeavour'd to find them out in the Crowd, and the Reſemblance of Cloaths deceiving her, she ſaid to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37055:25"/> 
               <hi>Florange,</hi> whom she took for <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, You betray me, Marquis, but Ile be reveng'd on Madam</hi> de Florange, <hi>though I were to die a moment after Florange</hi> knew the Citts voice again, and her Diſcourſe making an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon his Mind, that was but too ſuſceptible of jealouſie, he made way into the Crowd, without giving her one word of anſwer. The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen's Wife's Rage was inconceiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this occaſion; She imagin'd her ſelf abſolutely flighted, by the manner of his leaving her, and wiſh'd ſhe could extinguiſh her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in a moment; but not being able to effect that, ſhe turn'd all her thoughts to revenge.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs being ignorant of what paſs'd, did in a Corner enjoy one another's Converſation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dreaming, that love was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them any trouble. <hi>Florange</hi> ſought 'em over all, and finding them ſtept aſide, he perceiv'd his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37055:26"/> Fury to re-double. He had open'd his Mouth to ask them what they did there; but conſidering that the Busſle he might make, would retort upon himſelf, he made ſemblance of being ill, that he might have a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to go home. When he was come to his houſe, he bid his Wife prepare to leave <hi>Soiſſons</hi> on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row morning. She ask'd him the reaſon; but without vouchſafing to ſpecifie any thing, he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with letting her know, that he was not ſatisfy'd with her Conduct. She did not cloſe her Eyes all the Night long, making however leſs reflection on <hi>Florange</hi>'s anger, than on <hi>Mainville</hi>'s cruel ſeparation, ſhe beginning to love him more than her own Life. She lay contriving the means to bid him adieu; but not knowing how to do that, ſhe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to write to him as ſoon as it was day. In effect, ſhe was already thinking of having Pen and Paper, when a new Diſquiet did utterly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37055:26"/> confound her Repoſe. She knew not with whom to truſt her Letter, and thereby plainly ſaw, that it would be to no purpoſe for her to write. The day being come, ſhe began to ſlumber, when her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band told her, that for a perſon that was to take a journey, it became her not to ſleep ſo late. Whereupon he made her get out of Bed; after which he went into her Cloſet, and took thence her Ink and Paper, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he muſt rifle her of her Courtſhip, and deprive her of the means of letting her Lover hear from her.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs look'd upon him then after a ſcornful manner, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making him any reply; but ſhe loſt all her firmneſs when ſhe was to take Coach; then did ſhe revolve <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Deſpondency in her Mind, when he came to know of her Departure; and her Lover's Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction affected her more than her own Grief. However, as Love becomes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37055:27"/> the ſtronger by perſecution, ſhe quickly perceiv'd that ſhe lov'd him more than ſhe had ever yet lov'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body. After ſhe was come to their Countrey houſe, her Huſband ſuſpecting that ſhe would not reſt ſo contented, if the Love ſhe had for <hi>Mainville</hi> was in any wiſe ſtrong, he left her neither Ink nor Paper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides forbidding his people to give her any, though ſhe ask'd for it.</p>
            <p>While all this paſs'd in this manner, <hi>Mainville</hi> dreaming of nothing leſs than of what had happen'd, ſent a <hi>How d' ye</hi> to <hi>Florange</hi>'s Lodgings. The man he had encharg'd with this Meſſage being return'd thence, and having brought him back word, that he was gone that morning with his Wife, to return to his own houſe, ſurpriz'd him extreamly. He would believe nothing of it at firſt, but it having been confirm'd to him from another hand, he preſently judg'd, that ſo ſudden a departure was the effect of <hi>Florange</hi>'s Jealouſie. He
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37055:27"/> likewiſe fancy'd, that there was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly himſelf in the Town that he could ſix it upon. Thus he rejected his firſt thoughts, which ſuggeſted to him to run after his Miſtreſs. Then ſeeing that it would be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for him to ſtay any longer at <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> he reſolv'd to be gone to <hi>Paris,</hi> whence he had a deſign to ſend a man on purpoſe to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs. As he was juſt ready to take Horſe, the Citizen's Wife came to his Lodgings, all tranſported with Fury; for ſhe had newly been told, that he was juſt a going, without ſo much as bidding her farewell. She upbraided him with what ſhe had done for him, and his little acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for all, and forgot not to ſpeak of what had paſs'd the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before, accuſing him of being the moſt ungrateful of all men, in not vouchſafing ſo much as to take the pains to undeceive her. <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> being ſurpriz'd at this reproach, which he did not think he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37055:28"/> caus'd the thing to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd to him at length; and ſeeing that the Citt's miſtake had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd <hi>Florange</hi>'s Jealouſie, he made her no great reparation for his Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and on the contrary, treated her with ſufficient Contempt. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having diſmiſs'd her, he departed the Town, on the Road thinking only of the Marchioneſs, who on her ſide was only taken up with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. For without otherwiſe minding her Husband's rigours, who treated her with ſufficient indignity, and who had her watch'd by five or ſix perſons, to whom he had not been aſham'd to diſcover his Weakneſs; she wish'd for nothing elſe than to know what was become of <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville.</hi> Thus all her thoughts only tending that way, she took a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution difficult to form, but which was a ſtrong Proof of her Love. For forgetting all the allarms she had had by having confided her ſecret in <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> she conceiv'd a deſign
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37055:28"/> to make uſe of him to be the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>between</hi> of her and <hi>Mainville,</hi> and to let him hear from her. She knew not however what courſe to take to exact this Service from him, after what ſhe had ſaid to him; for ſhe dreaded his Reproaches. At length Love being ſtronger in her than any other Conſideration, ſhe conjur'd him, with Tears in her Eyes, to free her out of pain, and carry a Letter to her Lover. <hi>You love me, Grand-Champ,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>and I ſhall be glad to know it in this Occaſion. You'l make me die of Grief, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe me: whereas you'l reſtore me to Life by doing me this Service. It will coſt me mine, Madam,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> immediately, <hi>and you have the cruelty, to deſire that I ſhould die the moſt cruel Death imaginable. But no matter, ſince this must oblige you, it is for me to obey you without reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſhe had thus got his conſent, ſhe ask'd him for Paper and Ink; which he was oblig'd to furniſh her
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37055:29"/> withal accordingly. When ſhe had writ her Letter, ſhe gave it him, begging him to make diſpatch, that ſo <hi>Mainville</hi> might receive it before he arriv'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> whither ſhe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected him to be going. <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> all pierc'd with Grief, took it from her hands, and pretending ſome buſineſs, that he might get <hi>Florange</hi>'s leave, he mounted on Horſe-back, and overtook <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> half way. <hi>Mainville,</hi> whom the Marchioneſs had made the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Love, trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at her raſhneſs in truſting him with a matter of this conſequence; but at the ſame time admiring the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of this Domeſtick, he would needs embrace him, and ſpeak the ſence he had of ſo generous an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> retiring two ſteps back, to avoid his Careſſes, told him, that far from aſſuring him, that he was his Servant, he would franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell him, that there was not a man in the World, that he hated more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37055:29"/> than him; that he was well enough acquainted with the reaſon; and that if he had ſtoop'd ſo far as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him a Letter from the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs, he thought him poſſeſs'd of ſo much delicacy, as not to confound the Character of a paſſionate Lover, with that of an Unfortunate Rival: That he might judge of his Love by the inſtance he had newly giv'n of it, and the more this Love was violent, the more the effects of it were to be feared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi> took no notice that he heard his Menaces: and indeed far from ſhewing any reſentment, he did what he could to gain ſo generous a man, offering him a World of fine things, as of advancing him in War, and ſerving him with all his Credit. But all theſe Promiſes did not work upon <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> to do any thing that was low, maintaining his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity to the laſt. After this <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> made anſwer to the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and put his Letter into the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37055:30"/> hands of this Domeſtick. She had ſent him Word in hers, of what had been the Occaſion of her Departure, and how out of the deſire ſhe had to ſee him again, ſhe would rather feign ſome illneſs, that ſhe might go to the Waters of <hi>Bourbon.</hi> She was overjoy'd to hear, that <hi>Mainville</hi> would on his ſide be there; for ſo he aſſur'd her by his Letter, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſhe only diſcours'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> of her impatience till the ſeaſon of the Waters was come. <hi>The time betwixt this and that,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>will laſt me a thouſand years, and out of the fondneſs I am under, of ſeeing him again, there will not be a day but will ſeem longer than whole years to me. I own that hopes will in ſome manner eaſe my pain; but whatever Bleſſing I expect from ſo dear a ſight, I ſhall purchaſe it dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the uneaſineſſes I am going to be under, for fear he ſhould fail his Word. Grand-Champ,</hi> continu'd ſhe, <hi>May not the King march to his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37055:30"/> Conqueſts in the time of Waters, and doſt thou think that</hi> Mainville <hi>can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence himſelf from following him? Honour is a thing very nice in the Soul of a Man of Quality, and I am undone, if</hi> Mainville <hi>prefers it before his Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> hearken'd to all this with a Countenance wherein Deſpair and Rage ſeem'd to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over his Paſſion. Nay, and ſometimes was he juſt ready to load her with Reproaches, if by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn very uſual with Lovers, he had not been more afraid of vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her than of any thing elſe. However being no longer able to ſtay in the preſence of a Woman that ſet him a raving mad, he went his ways without ſaying a word to her. But ſhe was ſo poſſeſs'd with her Reflexions, that ſhe did not ſo much as take notice of what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him.</p>
            <p>When it was at length the ſeaſon of drinking the Waters, ſhe ask'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37055:31"/> her Husband leave to go thither, and he could not hanſomely refuſe her, becauſe ſhe had pretended to be ſick, having beſides ſlily engag'd the Phyſicians to ſay that ſhe ſtood in need of them for her recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Nevertheleſs <hi>Florange</hi> being reſolv'd not to leave her one ſtep, made ſemblance on his ſide, that the Waters would be good for him, and went along with her. The Marchioneſſes ſpite was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in this Occaſion, and if ſhe had durſt, ſhe had let it fly out to ſtrange Extremities. She then fell to thinking how to break off this Journey; but making reflexion, that ſo doing would but too clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt her Intrigue, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to advertiſe <hi>Mainville</hi> of what occur'd, that he might take his meaſures for his ſeeing her on the Road.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was again encharg'd to carry him this News; and having accordingly done it with the ſame
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37055:31"/> fidelity he had exerted the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Mainville</hi> took Horſe for <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>targis,</hi> and ſtay'd in the beſt Inn, where the Marchioneſs had writ him word ſhe was to lodg. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he had no other Train than a <hi>Valet de Chambre;</hi> and for the obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating all ſuſpicion, in caſe he ſtaid there any time, he pretended to be ſick, that he might at freedom wait the Marchioneſſes coming. Two days after, ſhe arriv'd there with her Huſband; and no ſooner was ſhe alighted, but that ſhe gave <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> order to acquaint <hi>Mainville,</hi> that ſhe was deſirous to ſee him. <hi>Mainville</hi> told <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> that could not be till after her Husband was gone to Bed; and as the Marchioneſs did not lie with him, they would have all ſort of leiſure of converſing together. When <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had giv'n this account to the Marchioneſs, <hi>Ah my God!</hi> cry'd ſhe, <hi>That's impoſſible: How ſee me by Night? That's ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37055:32"/> his own ruin, and the ruining of my ſelf. What would</hi> Florange <hi>ſay if he came to know it? and would there after that be any mercy for me? What ſay you,</hi> Grand-Champ? <hi>give me good advice in this matter. Grand-Champ,</hi> being enrag'd at what he did, and what he was ſtill oblig'd to hear, anſwer'd not a word; but ſeeing that ſhe preſs'd him to tell her his Opinion; <hi>How, Madam,</hi> he reply'd to her, <hi>Ought you not to be ſatisfy'd with what I here do, but you muſt needs conſtrain me to diſcourſe you upon a thing of this nature? And to what purpoſe would it be for me to diſſwade you from ſeeing the Marquis</hi> de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville, <hi>ſince you will not follow my advice? Why will I not follow it,</hi> the Marchioneſs anſwer'd; <hi>and ſhould I not be glad, that you would let me ſee that it was impoſſible to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him this ſatisfaction. No, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, it is not impoſſible,</hi> reply'd <hi>Grand-Champ, ſince that you doubt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37055:32"/> of it, and you will infallibly ſee him in your Chamber, ſince you only deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate to know whether the thing be feaſible or not. I thought you would have declin'd it out of fear of wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your honour; but the happy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis triumphs over your Scruples. You at firſt told me, you meant to ſhun him, with ſuch a World of Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and now you are no longer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of ſingling him out to a private Rendezvouze. Ah,</hi> Grand-Champ, <hi>you are mistaken,</hi> the Marchioneſs anſwer'd, <hi>and if he comes into my Chamber, I mean not, that you ſhall go one ſtep from me, that ſo you your ſelf may be a Witneſs, that nothing ſhall there paſs, but what's honeſt; and that though I be wanting to Decency, I at leaſt am not wanting to Virtue. No, 'tis you that are mistaken, Madam,</hi> cry'd <hi>Grand-Champ, if you believe you can be wanting to Decorum, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being wanting to Virtue; for there is ſuch a connexion between them two, that a perſon can no longer be ſaid to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37055:33"/> be innocent, when ſhe has once fail'd in her Conduct, It is for you to make reflexion thereupon; and if it proves my misfortune, that my Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will nothing avail, you need only ſay what you deſire of me: I will ſtill bring, if you order me, this happy Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, into your very Chamber; but do not oblige me to be preſent at a Converſation that would make me mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had made her theſe offers, ſhe took him at his Word, conjuring him to pay her this Service. She no longer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted for him to be preſent in the Room with <hi>Mainville;</hi> and this Circumſtance caſt him into the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Deſpondency; for he fram'd ſuch things in his imagination as ſhe did not in the leaſt dream of; and which his Jealouſie nevertheleſs made him think to be real. The Marchioneſſes Chamber was at the end of a Gallery; and there was a kind of <hi>Anti-chamber,</hi> where <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37055:33"/> had Orders to lye. The Marquis <hi>de Florange</hi> having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to watch his Wife's Conduct ſo narrowly, as that he might be able to give an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it. Thus it lay in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to let in whom he pleas'd; and the exceſs of his love requiring him to pay this Service to his Rival, he introduc'd him into the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Chamber, and ſhut the door upon them. While <hi>Mainville</hi> was there, an Adventure happen'd in the Inn, that made them both more than a little uneaſie. One of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants being in Love with the Maid, and fancying he had perceiv'd ſome Bowels of kindneſs in her towards him, he ſtole ſoftly into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and made her ſtart out of her ſleep. This Wench being honeſt, beyond what is ordinary in thoſe of her ſtamp, being to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree ſurpriz'd at his inſolence, gave then a great Scream, which put all the houſe into allarum. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37055:34"/> 
               <hi>de Florange</hi> awak'd at this noiſe, as well as the reſt, and having heard how the caſe ſtood, he was heard to cry out aloud, <hi>kill him, kill him.</hi> For he had a natural averſion for all thoſe that endeavour'd to debauch other mens Wives; fearing, that if he appear'd indulgent upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, it might give ſome Gallant the Boldneſs to ſparkle it to his. His Voice immediately ſtruck <hi>Mainvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le</hi>'s and the Marchioneſſes Ears; and <hi>Mainville</hi> thinking it was him he meant, drew his Sword at the ſame time, telling the Marchioneſs, that it would not be ſo eaſie a matter as was imagin'd, to take away his Life. At theſe Words he broke out of her Arms, that graſp'd him ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, as if ſhe meant to bid him a laſt farewell, and ruſhing out of the Chamber, he ran towards the place where he heard <hi>Florange</hi> a talking. When he was got to the end of the Gallery, he perceiv'd him in his Night-Gown, by the Light of a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37055:34"/> Candle, which a Lacquey held be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. This Lackquey no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſaw <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Sword glitter, but that he let fall the Candle out of fear, at the ſame time giving a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Schriek. <hi>Florange,</hi> for his part made haſte into his Chamber, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving likewiſe perceiv'd the Sword; inſomuch that <hi>Mainville</hi> finding no body to diſpute the paſſage with him, he entred his own Room, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Florange</hi>'s being able to ſay, who had put him to ſo great a fright.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being under a moſt doleful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet for what would happen to <hi>Mainville,</hi> went out into the Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to liſten; but coming to know, that the noiſe that had been made in the Inn, had been occaſion'd by the Man and Maids Adventure; and hearing no talk of her Lover, ſhe diſpers'd her fears. After this <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> advis'd her to go to Bed, that if her Husband ſhould by chance come into her Chamber, he might
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37055:35"/> not ask why ſhe had ſate up ſo late. Hardly was ſhe undrefs'd, but that <hi>Florange,</hi> who had had time to call all his People to his ſuccours, came, and knock'd at her Door, with ſuch a noiſe, that a body would have ſaid, he meant to break it open. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> went and open'd it; and the firſt thing <hi>Florange</hi> ask'd him, was, if a man did not go out of his Chamber with his Sword in his hand. He made him anſwer, that no body could go out there, ſince the Door had been always ſhut, and that if he had not heard his Voice, he would not have open'd it. After this, <hi>Florange</hi> knock'd at his Wife's Chamber-door; and there ſhe made him wait for ſome time, to make him believe that ſhe was in a deep ſleep. At laſt ſhe made ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of awaking her Woman, that was a Confident of her Intrigue, and who had been preſent all the while <hi>Mainville</hi> ſtaid with her. <hi>Florange</hi> tax'd 'em both with their ſleeping ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37055:35"/> faſt, after they had aſſur'd him, they heard not the leaſt of all the noiſe that had been made in the Inn.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Florange</hi> had left his Wife, he made reflexion upon the Viſion he had had of the Sword, and relying upon what <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had ſaid to him, he fancy'd the man to have come out of ſome of the next Chambers to that of the Marchioneſs. Thus all was appeas'd in the Inn; after which all fell aſleep again, as if nothing had happen'd. There was only <hi>Mainville,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, and <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> that could not be of thoſe that taſted of Reſt; for their Amour furniſh'd them with ſufficient matter of anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. As for <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to judge he was over-whelm'd with grief, and that he could not think of his cruel Deſtiny, without believing himſelf the moſt unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of all men. As to <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs, though they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37055:36"/> ought to be ſo ſatisfy'd, being ſure of one anothers Love, yet they had great cauſe of vexation. They had hop'd to have enjoy'd one anothers Company for a whole Night toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and an unhappy Adventure of a Man and a Maid, had diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their hopes. Beſides, they knew not when they might ſee one another again; for as they had not had the leiſure to take their meaſures toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Mainville</hi> was upon the point of returning to the Army, and the danger he was going to run, did extraordinarily allarum his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The Day being come, <hi>Florange</hi> and his Wife continued their way; and being arriv'd at <hi>Bourbon,</hi> they took the Waters, of which they had no great need. But as it is not the ſame thing with thoſe Waters, as with the Water of the <hi>Seine,</hi> which one may drink of, without fear of injuring ones ſelf, they ſpoil'd their Stomacks, either that they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37055:36"/> a Diſpoſition thereunto, or that God thought fitting to puniſh them for feigning to be ſick. Their Indiſpoſition began with a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſtion, which at firſt hinder'd them from ſleeping, and a <hi>Fever</hi> coming thereupon, it was fear'd this Malady might have ill Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thus for prevention, they had recourſe to the moſt able Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; but they exhauſted their whole Knowledg, without giving any eaſe to their Patients. This occaſion'd their Friends to begin to deſpair of their Health. The Marquis <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> was then at the Army, whither he went after the adventure of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgis.</hi> The Marchioneſs, thinking her ſelf at the Extremity, ſignify'd to him the ſtate ſhe was in; and he had no ſooner learnt this ill News, but that he reſolv'd to go ſee her, let what would come on't. There was no room for his deſiring leave. The King granted none: Wherefore he pretended himſelf ſick, that he might
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37055:37"/> have a pretence to be carry'd into a Neighbouring Town. As ſoon as he was there arriv'd, he won the heart of his Landlord, and of a Phyſician, and prevail'd with them to give out, that he was in great danger; inſomuch, that when any one came to pay him a Viſit, they ſaid, he was not to be ſeen, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Violence of his Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. His Servants had alſo Order to remain bare-headed in his Room, and when any Perſons came to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after his Health, they made them anſwer ſoftly at the Door, as if they had been afraid of diſturbing his Head. In the mean while <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> having taken his meaſures thus well, went away Poſt in the dusk of the Evening, and repair'd to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> where the Marchioneſs <hi>de Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> was ſick. He ſaw her by <hi>Grand Champ</hi>'s means, and found her in better Health than he expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For her Diſtemper, when juſt upon the point of tumbling her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37055:37"/> her Grave, was diminiſh'd all on the ſudden; and but that her looks ſpoke her to have been ill, a man would hardly have believ'd it, ſo well was ſhe recover'd. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſes joy was great, to ſee ſo ſignal an inſtance of her Lover's Paſſion. She embrac'd him with an extraordinary tenderneſs, and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Careſſes, teſtify'd ſhe could never ſufficiently expreſs her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville,</hi> who was as fooliſh as are all people that are in Love, was charm'd with her affection, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected his Duty; inſomuch that he was now but little afraid of his Cheat coming to be detected. Thus giving all his Thoughts, and all his Cares to his Miſtreſs, his contrivance lay only how to be daily with her; in which he found nevertheleſs ſome difficulty, becauſe that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was to depart that very Evening, to go into <hi>Picardy,</hi> whither he was ſent by <hi>Florange.</hi> Nevertheleſs, to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37055:38"/> return after having ſeen her but once, was a thing he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve on, finding he had hazarded too much to have ſuch ſcanty ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. In fine, after having one while liſten'd to his Reaſon, which adviz'd him to return to the Army, and another while his Paſſion, that thwarted thoſe Intentions, this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter got the Aſcendant, and he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy'd the means of getting to ſpeak, at leaſt once again with his Miſtreſs, For that purpoſe he dreſs'd himſelf up as a Phyſician, and under that Habit he had free admittance into her Chamber, without needing any body to introduce him. Though that his Features were too deeply engrav'd in the Marchioneſſes mind, for her to miſtake him, yet the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of that Lady was extream, when he took her by the Arm, to feel her Pulſe. She immediately dimiſs'd all the Servants out of the Room, except her Woman, whom ſhe did not ſuſpect. Then giving
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37055:38"/> 
               <hi>Mainville</hi> a ſtrong Reprimand, for expoſing himſelf and her too to ſuch a danger, ſhe forbid him to venture ſo again, telling him, that he ought; at leaſt, to advertiſe her of his Diſguiſe, to prevent her firſt ſurpriſe. <hi>Mainville</hi> excus'd himſelf the beſt he could, rejecting all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Love, and upon his not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving known that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was to be gone till after he had left her. After this Converſation, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan an other, extreamly tender; and as they were going to engage deeply into amorous ſoftneſſes, the Marchioneſſes uſual Phyſician came in, who was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd to find an other Phyſician at the ſick Beauties Beds-head. His Cheeks glow'd for meer anger, thinking that he was ſlighted. He ask'd <hi>Mainville,</hi> by whoſe Order he came thither, he whom he did not know to be of the Faculty of <hi>Paris. Mainville</hi> was ſtrangely <hi>non plus'd</hi> at his Queſtion, ſeeing how furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37055:39"/> he was upon the matter: But making a Vertue of Neceſſity, he reply'd, that he went no where without being ſent for: That though he was not of the Faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> yet he was not the leſs expert; and that the Phyſicians of <hi>Montpelier</hi> did in nothing come ſhort of all the Phyſicians of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>There is a certain Antipathy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Phyſicians of <hi>Paris,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Montpelier,</hi> inſomuch that this Diſcourſe ſtill augmented the uſual Phyſician's Reſentment. He took fire at the ſame time, and after having diſcharg'd his Choler againſt this new Doctor, he told the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, that ſince ſhe put ſo much Confidence in an ignorant Fellow, ſhe might make uſe of him, and that it was the laſt time he would viſit her. Nevertheleſs, upon his going away, he went to <hi>Florange</hi>'s Chamber, where his heart being full of what had befallen him, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37055:39"/> of the Affront that was done him. <hi>Florange</hi> was ſtill ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſick, being nothing ſo near his recovery as his Wife was to hers. For he had ſtill daily Tranſports in his Brain, that made him rave; but being the moſt jealous of all men, he immediately diſtruſted the <hi>Montplier</hi> Phyſician, and to ſee if he was not miſtaken, he at the ſame time took his Night-Gown, and went into his Wives Chamber. On the way he told the Doctor, that it was for his ſake that he took this pains, as being willing to conceal his Jealouſie. The Doctor was ſo tranſported with Anger, that he made not any effort to hinder him; and though he knew well enough in his mind, that ſtirring out of his Bed did not befit his preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, yet he was over-joy'd that he had this ſatisfaction given him. <hi>He'l be your Death,</hi> ſaid he to him as they went along, <hi>if you make uſe of him. He is but a meer Quack,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37055:40"/> and that you'l preſently perceive by his Meen.</hi> As he entertain'd him with ſuch like Diſcourſes, to animate him the more, they entred the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Chamber; and <hi>Florange</hi>'s ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe was extraordinary, when he found that the Phyſician of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelier,</hi> and the Marquis <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> were but one and the ſame thing. <hi>How,</hi> cry'd he at the ſame time, <hi>the Marquis</hi> de Mainville <hi>is turn'd Doctor! How can that be, and ſince when is this</hi> Metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis? <hi>I muſt be reveng'd, and offer up to my reſentment a Friend that ruines me, and triumphs over my Honour.</hi> At this Name of <hi>Mainville,</hi> which was univerſally known, the true Phyſician remain'd as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded as <hi>Florange:</hi> for he then plainly ſaw he had committed a great miſtake, in diſcovering what but for him had been conceal'd. He trembled for fear, knowing how dangerous it was to incur the Indignation of a man of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37055:40"/> Wherefore he would have given all he had to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triev'd the Blunder he had made.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, <hi>Mainville</hi> and his Miſtreſs were no leſs afraid than the Doctor; but Love, which was the firſt cauſe of this Diſorder, ſince it was it that had induc'd <hi>Mainville</hi> to put himſelf into a Diſguiſe, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted a thing to <hi>Mainville,</hi> that freed them both out of perplexity. He began to ſeize upon the Marquis <hi>de Florange,</hi> crying, that his Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy took him; and that if they did not carry him back to Bed, it was capable of being his Death. He at the ſame time trode upon the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian's Foot; and he underſtanding what this meant, joyn'd with him to make the poor <hi>Florange</hi> believe, that he was very ill. <hi>Good Lord! what a furious tranſport,</hi> cry'd the Doctor at the ſame time, <hi>to take a Phyſician for a Marquis, and to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him alſo of attempting upon his Honour. My Lord, you must drink
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37055:41"/> a refreſhing Ptiſanne, or elſe you are a loſt man. Florange</hi> was terribly enrag'd at this Diſcourſe, as not over-well knowing whether he rav'd or not. However, the two Phyſicians, his Wife, and her Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ceas'd not dragging of him into his own Room, and putting him to Bed again in ſpight of his teeth. Then had he a real Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy, holding a thouſand extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Diſcourſes. The Phyſician of <hi>Montpelier</hi> took that time to bid the Company farewel; and the Marchioneſs ſaw him depart with leſs regret; judging, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what had happen'd, it would be putting him into too evident a danger, and her ſelf too for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Mainville</hi> was gone away, he went to his Houſe who writes the <hi>Gazet;</hi> where in conſideration of ſome money, he had inſerted, that he was extream ſick in the Town where he was thought to be,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37055:41"/> and that there was no longer any hopes of his Life. From thence he went to <hi>Florange</hi>'s Phyſician, to whom he ſaid, that he pardon'd him for having hamper'd him in ſo unlucky a buſineſs, provided he would maintain to the very laſt, what he had ſo well began. He thereupon acquainted him with what he had newly done, that ſo he might diſabuſe <hi>Florange,</hi> if he continued to affirm, that he was paulm'd upon by his Wife. He told him, that the <hi>Gazet</hi> was to be vended the next day throughout the City, and that this fell out ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pat for their purpoſe. After this, he went his ways for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, where there was not the leaſt ſuſpicion of all the Pranks he came from playing. <hi>Florange</hi>'s Fit went away, having laſted full Fourteen Hours. He ſent for a Kinſman of his Wives, to whom he made his Complaints upon what had befallen him the Evening before, telling
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37055:42"/> him, that he could not keep her after this. This man, who by chance, had read the <hi>Gazet</hi> in the morning, and knew beſides that <hi>Florange</hi> had raved all the Night, imagin'd at his hearing him talk of <hi>Mainville,</hi> that he was ſtill in his raving Fit. Thus without anſwering to his Diſcourſe, he told him, that he was only to be fed with good Broths, that ſo he might be brought to his right Senſes, and his Head ſetled. But <hi>Florange</hi> burſting out into anger; <hi>My Head,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>is too ſick ever to be ſetled; and I wonder that you, who are my Relation, as well as Madam</hi> de Florange's, <hi>would make me believe, that I am a Viſionary fellow. You are ſo in truth, if there ever was one,</hi> this Kinſman anſwer'd, <hi>to conceive a jealouſie of a man, who at this hour is not perhaps alive.</hi> Mainville <hi>has been ſick a long time, and the ſtate he is in, does with a Vengeance hinder him from thinking
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37055:42"/> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Wife. Take my Word, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, if you mean to fall out with her, uſe at leaſt a more probable pretext than this; for you'l have no body on your ſide, as long as you have this only to ſay against her.</hi> Thereupon the wonted Phyſician entred, who had provided himſelf with a <hi>Gazet;</hi> and <hi>Florange</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take him for Witneſs, that he affirm'd nothing but what was true, had the confuſion to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtill accus'd of raving. <hi>You think not of what you ſay, My Lord,</hi> ſaid this Phyſician to him; <hi>'tis the Remains of your Diſtemper that make you talk in this manner: The Marquis</hi> de Mainville <hi>lies at the utmoſt extremity; and if he dies, it will be a great loſs to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi> Thereupon he took the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zet</hi> out of his Pocket, and read a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud the Article concerning this Marquis. After this he highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll'd his Noble Actions; adding, that he might have puſh'd on his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37055:43"/> Fortune much farther, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haſty a Death. <hi>Florange</hi>'s con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was great, after reading of the <hi>Gazet.</hi> He began to believe, that the violence of his Malady was the occaſion of his Suſpicions; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having more and more confirm'd himſelf in this Opinion, becauſe that his Kinſman, and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, ſtill continued to tell him the ſame thing, at length he was ſo well perſwaded, that he ask d the former pardon for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints he had made to him.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs had been thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto under extraordinary fear; but being inform'd by her Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that her Huſband began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his having tax'd her, ſhe quickly diſmiſs'd her apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The reſt of the Summer was ſpent without furniſhing her with any other Adventure; and her Huſband being quite out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſhe went along with him to their Countrey-houſe. About the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37055:43"/> beginning of <hi>Autumn</hi> they took a journey to our Lady of <hi>Lieſſe,</hi> in acknowledgment of their Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and Devotion having ſpirited <hi>Mainville</hi> to go thither at his return from the Campaign, he accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly met them as they were in the Church. <hi>Mainville</hi> made no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of accoſting <hi>Florange,</hi> twit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him with his going from <hi>Soiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> without bidding him adieu. <hi>Florange</hi> was in a rage, that he was oblig'd to ſuffer his Converſation: Thus he receiv'd him coldly: but <hi>Mainville</hi> having perceiv'd it, made as if he had urgent Buſineſs; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he himſelf freed him out of perplexity, by re-mounting on Horſe back. By this means he had not time to diſcourſe the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs; but his eyes finding her more beauteous than ever, they explain'd to her in one moment all that he had to ſay to her. After he was gone, <hi>Florange</hi> re-calling all his <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's</hi> into his memory, took it ill,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37055:44"/> that he ſhould meet 'em ſo pat at our Lady of <hi>Lieſſe.</hi> He imagin'd, that this could not fall out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his being advertiz'd; and in his heart he accus'd the Marchioneſs of it. After having perform'd his Devotions in that Church, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his own home, and on the Road ſpoke not ſo much as one Word to his Wife; ſo ſpighted was he at this Adventure. When he was come thither, he entertain'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> with the Encounter he had had, and declar'd to him his Suſpicions. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> jump'd with him in his Opinion; but yet endeavour'd to undeceive him, that he might not expoſe the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to vexatious Reproaches. He was ſtill over Head and Ears in Love with her; inſomuch, that this Lady coming on her ſide to tell him, how Chance had brought <hi>Mainville</hi> and her to an Interview, when ſhe leaſt expected it. <hi>That was no hard matter, Madam,</hi> ſaid
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37055:44"/> he to her; <hi>and when one is of intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence with chance, things ſtill more ſurprizing happen out.</hi> The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs being amaz'd at the freedom he took of making her Reproaches, told him after a diſdainful manner, that it became indeed ſuch a man as he to intermeddle in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: That now ſhe plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her miſtake, when ſhe thought him an honeſt man; and that all Servants return'd ſooner or later to their Character. It is impoſſible to expreſs how diſmally the amorous <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was mortify'd with this word Servant. He had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to imagin'd he might one day come to touch the Marchioneſs, if ſhe once came to make reflection of all he did for her: But loſing all hopes after this laſt inſtance of her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, he left her with his heart full of rage. <hi>No, ſhe does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> ſaid he to himſelf, <hi>the eſteem of a worthy man: She's a meer Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, that's won by a gaudy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37055:45"/> and I ought to indulge my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, unleſs I mean to paſs for the most faint-hearted of all Lovers. I ſerve a Rival, to pleaſe him; I rack my ſelf to death, as a body may ſay, to ſerve the man in the World I most hate; I eſpouſe the intereſts of that ungrateful Woman, to make her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band believe, that he has a Wife ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream diſcreet; yet for my reward ſhe calls me Servant.—No, I cannot think on't without burſting into a Fury; and either I have no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my mind, or I ſhall quickly forget her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf with this Diſcourſe, and much other ſtuff of the like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that expreſs'd the exceſs of his Reſentment, word was brought him, that a man enquir'd for him; and going to ſee who it was, it was found to be a Perſon from <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Marquis had made a ſtop at <hi>Villers-Cotterets,</hi> whence he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37055:45"/> to his Miſtreſs. His Meſſenger having preſented his Letter to <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> beſought him to make an anſwer as ſoon as poſſible to his Maſter. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd a moment after, and told the Meſſenger, that <hi>Mainville</hi> might come about midnight, and that he ſhould find the Park-door open: That the Marchioneſs had not had time to write to him; but that this was ſufficient. This man made haſte to return; and when half way, he met <hi>Mainville,</hi> who was ſo impatient to know if the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would accept of a Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouze, that he required of her by his Letter, that he was mounted on Horſe-back, to avail himſelf of it the ſooner. This Meſſenger gave him an account of what <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had ſaid to him; but at the ſame time adviz'd him to turn back, ſaying, that he ſeem'd to be in a ſtrange Concern when he gave him his Anſwer; and that either he was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37055:46"/> miſtaken, or that it was not ſafe to truſt to his Word. <hi>Mainville</hi> made a mock of his fear, and continued on his way. But this Meſſenger was not ſo much miſtaken as <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> imagin'd. For indeed <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> finding that this occaſion was favourable to revenge himſelf of the Marchioneſſes ſlights, had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Florange,</hi> in the firſt Heat of his Reſentment, letting him by that ſee that his Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions were not over-ill grounded. Nevertheleſs, he was cautious of telling him, that he was the Party that had carry'd on the Intrigues of theſe Lovers to the point it was at. Far from this, he made him believe, that this Letter was fallen by chance into his hands; and that he had no ſooner ſeen what it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, but that he had deliver'd it to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Florange</hi> being aſcertain'd of his Diſhonour, or at leaſt, that he was robb'd of his Wife's Heart, did not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37055:46"/> heſitate one moment, as to being reveng'd. He, with <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> reſolv'd to ſurprize <hi>Mainville</hi> in his Wife's Chamber, and ſacrifice them both to his Reſentment. In the mean time <hi>Mainville</hi> ſtill advanc'd, not in the leaſt dreaming of what was brewing againſt him. He found the Park-door open, as <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had ſent him word, and ſlipping between a Paliſade, he got to the Houſe-door, which was half open. <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> the better to make him fall into the Trap that was laid for him, had not only deſcrib'd the Houſe to the Meſſenger, but had likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to ſtand behind this laſt Door, whence he was to convey <hi>Mainville</hi> into the Marchioneſſes Room. He had likewiſe told this Lady, that <hi>Mainville</hi> was to come to her, that ſhe might leave her Door open. Her eagerneſs to ſee him again, had made her fall into the Snare, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out requiring other aſſurance than
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37055:47"/> 
               <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Word. When <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> was come to the Houſe-door, he really found this Domeſtick, who conducted him as far as the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſſes Room, whoſe Door he found. <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> after that, withdrew; but by a ſurprizing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, he, who only breath'd Revenge, ſince the Marchioneſs had treated him ill, found himſelf mov'd with Compaſſion, revolving in his mind the unhappy Condition to which ſhe was going to be reduc'd. In ſhort, his Love got the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in a moment. His Eyes were all bath'd in Tears, out of Grief for having been the Cauſe of ſo lovely a Perſon's Death; and in a word, if nothing was to do, but to give her the very laſt Drop of his Blood, to repair what he had done, he would willingly have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it.</p>
            <p>In the mean while he was to give an Anſwer to <hi>Florange,</hi> who had planted himſelf behind a Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſade
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37055:47"/> of Maple to ſee <hi>Mainville</hi> paſs. This Huſband had heard him as he ſlipt by between the Trees: Nay, and had ſeen him; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that growing weary of ſtaying any longer in that place, ſince it was time to come to ſlaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he went his way, to know what detain'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> from coming to give him notice. He found this Unfortunate Domeſtick Twenty Paces from his Ambuſcade; and having ask'd him, whether he had conducted <hi>Mainville</hi> above Stairs, he made anſwer, No; and that he muſt needs have fail'd the Aſſignation. <hi>Prethee, why that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me,</hi> reply'd <hi>Florange</hi> in anger; <hi>for I ſaw him paſs by where I was.</hi> At theſe words he would have gone up into the Marchioneſſes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; but <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> ſtopping him by the Arm, told him, that his going might cauſe him to miſs his aim; that it was convenient for him to go up firſt, to ſee if <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:37055:48"/> was there; that he would come and give him an account at the bottom of the Stairs; and that afterwards it would be for him not to loſe the occaſion of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd. <hi>Florange,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greatneſs of the Offence, could not yet put off a certain I ear that was natural to him. Thus being willing that any other than himſelf ſhould make the firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he comply'd with all <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> propos'd, and ſtaid for him at the bottom of the Stairs. <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> ſeeing this, mounted above, without loſing of time; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving caus'd the Door to be open'd, he extreamly ſurpriz'd theſe Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, when he told them all was ruin'd. Being ſeiz'd with Fear, they ask'd him what had fallen out: But <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done than they, made anſwer, that it was not a time to hold long Diſcourſes, and that <hi>Mainville</hi> muſt be gone at the very inſtant, if he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37055:48"/> meant to be alive a Quarter of an Hour after. That he would find <hi>Florange</hi> at the bottom of the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe; and that to paſs ſafely, he muſt counterfeit his Voice, and tell him, that now is the time for you to be reveng'd. That he could ſay nothing more to him at preſent, and that another time he would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravel this myſtery unto him.</p>
            <p>At theſe words he took <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> by the Arm, to ſhove him out, conjuring him to make his eſcape, and at the ſame time to ſave the Marchioneſſes Honour and Life. As this Diſcourſe was too preſſing to loſe time in deliberation, he did not ſtand upon much entreaty: Down ſtole he as ſoftly as he could, holding by the Rails, and finding <hi>Florange</hi> at the bottom, who ſtopp'd him, he whiſper'd in his Ear what <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had ſaid to him. <hi>Florange</hi> heard thoſe words diſtinctly, but did not know his Voice; inſomuch, that think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37055:49"/> to find <hi>Mainville</hi> above, he mounted haſtily, breathing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Revenge. <hi>Mainville</hi> had left the Marchioneſſes Chamber-Door open, and <hi>Florange</hi> entring therein, with a Piſtol in one Hand, and a Sword in the other, he ſought for <hi>Mainville,</hi> as the firſt Victim he ought to offer up to his Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He was much amaz'd to ſee only <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> leaning againſt a Table, and the Marchioneſs on the other ſide, not having the power to ſupport her ſelf. <hi>Where am I,</hi> cry'd he at this ſight, <hi>and what's become of</hi> Mainville? <hi>Speak</hi> Grand-Champ: <hi>did you not tell me he was here, and coming up after me, how came you to be in this Chamber? Grand Champ</hi> being prepar'd for all that <hi>Florange</hi> could ſay to him, and reſolv'd to ſave the Marchioneſſes Life at the expence of his own, look'd upon him fixedly, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing his Speech to him: <hi>Kill me, my Lord,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>ſince
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37055:49"/> I have deſerved Death: I am the greateſt Cheat of all men, in having falſely accus'd my Lady. I have made you conceive a falſe Opinion of her Vertue, by forging to you a Letter from</hi> Mainville, <hi>to induce you to uſe her ill: And what is ſtill beyond all this, is, that Love is the occaſion of all theſe Crimes. There is not any other man, ſave I,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued he, <hi>that had any intentions to ſeduce her: And if I had brought them about, I ſhould not have been ſo enrag'd, to undertake to make you ſhed a Blood that ought to be ſo dear to you. I now perceive my fault; and to puniſh me for it, you need only to pierce my Boſome.</hi> At the ſame time he preſented himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, offering himſelf to a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Death: But <hi>Florange</hi> not being able to reconcile theſe Words with what had been told him at the bottom of the Stair-caſe; <hi>Do you kill me,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>or free me out of pain, by acquainting me, how
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37055:50"/> you came hither before me, and what is become of him that ſpoke to me before that I came up. No body can have ſpoke to you,</hi> reply'd <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> faintly; <hi>and through a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſion of your Paſſion, you imagin'd you heard what no body can have ſaid to you. The ſincere confeſſion I have made t' ye of my fault, ought to convince you of it: for I would not expoſe my ſelf to your Reſentment for an other. It is I alone that am culpable; and Madam</hi> de Florange, <hi>and the Marquis</hi> de Mainville <hi>are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs at firſt could not imagine the meaning of all this; but beginning to apprehend ſomething, ſhe broke ſilence, to complain of her Husband's Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if he had really been migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily in the wrong, to doubt of her Vertue. So as that poor <hi>Florange</hi> being in Deſpondency at ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary an Adventure, withdrew into his own Apartment, without
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37055:50"/> having the power to take any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. After this <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> made the Marchioneſs a ſincere Confeſſion of his fault; and as he was penetrated with regret, he would in her preſence have run himſelf through with his Sword; telling her, that he could no longer live, after having ſo mortally of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended her. But the Marchioneſs leaping upon him, hinder'd him from executing his fatal Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and promis'd him never to call his Crime to mind. <hi>I ſhall have it in mind, Madam,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>all my life long; but now it ſhall not be ſo long, ſo as I may weary my ſelf much in the World.</hi> At theſe words he went out of her Chamber after a deſperate ſort of manner, and without conſidering that it was Night, he took the firſt way he found, and did not ſtop till it was day. The Marquis <hi>de Mainville</hi> had taken exactly the ſame Road, and Fortune would have it, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37055:51"/> they ſhould both alight in the ſame Inn. <hi>Mainville</hi> had newly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd away a man to <hi>Florange</hi>'s Caſtle, to know what had occur'd there after his departure; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> could inform him the beſt of any body, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him, that he would free him out of pain, and tell him all he did not know. <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy his Curioſity, gave him a long account of the Marchioneſſes ſlight, and of the revenge he deſign'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her: and continuing the reſt of his Story, he acquainted him how when upon the point of ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them both, his Love for the Marchioneſs had ſav'd them. <hi>Alas!</hi> then cry'd <hi>Mainville, I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have ſuſpected you of Treachery. On the contrary, I had ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in you, that I have juſt now ſent a Letter to you for the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy that I am; I have perhaps deſtroy'd your labour: You had ſet her Husband's mind to rights
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37055:51"/> by your Addreſs; or at leaſt, you had left him in an uncertainty of his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; and my imprudence has ſpoyl'd All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had told his Story after ſo unconcern'd a manner, that he ſeem'd now a Party indifferent; but hearing to what danger <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> had expos'd the Marchioneſs, he ſeem'd to recover new Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>You are really very unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>in cauſing ſo much trouble to a Lady, who would ever have been innocent, had ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known you. I ought neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to be glad, that ſhe has occaſion to complain of you, that ſo ſhe may forget you: But as in this occaſion her All is at ſtake, I ſhall here wait for the return of your man, that ſo if he has put your Letter into any other hands than hers, I may ſtill render her a piece of Service.</hi> He had no ſooner ſpoke theſe words, but in came that man, being a Peaſant that <hi>Mainville</hi> had been forc'd to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37055:52"/> employ, as having none of his own Servants with him, to whom he could give this Commiſſion. They ask'd him both at the ſame time, what was become of the Letter; and the Bumpkin anſwer'd them, that he had giv'n it to <hi>Grand-Champ. What ſort of man is he,</hi> cry'd <hi>Mainville</hi> immediately, all in Deſpair at his miſtake? <hi>He is tall,</hi> reply'd the Peaſant, <hi>well made, and very neat.</hi> He then gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Perſon to whom he had deliver'd his Letter; and <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> and <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> knew plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Pourtraict of him, that it was fall'n into <hi>Florange</hi>'s Hands. Thereupon <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Mainville</hi> to lend him his Horſe; for he was come a-foot; telling him, that he was going to pay the Marchioneſs the laſt Service he ſhould pay her as long as he liv'd. <hi>Mainville</hi> gave him his Horſe; and <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> uſing diſpatch, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd to the Houſe of a Peaſant of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37055:52"/> 
               <hi>Florange</hi>'s Village, and there wrote a Letter. He then encharg'd the Peaſant with it, with order to put it into the Marchioneſſes own Hands, as a thing of the higheſt Conſequence. This Peaſant did dexterouſly acquit himſelf of his Commiſſion; ſo as that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs was advertiz'd of the fault <hi>Mainville</hi> had committed, and to make timely Proviſion for her ſelf.</p>
            <p>She receiv'd this Advice juſt in the nick: for her Husband deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to convict her of her Intrigue from her own writing, had newly caus'd <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Letter to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to her under hand, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that ſhe would make an Anſwer to it. And indeed ſhe had already Ink and Paper to do it, when that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Letter made her change her ſtile. Inſtead of writing to <hi>Mainville,</hi> as ſhe was going to do, ſhe writ to her Husband; and leaving the Letter
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37055:53"/> upon her Table, ſhe went to find out <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> whom ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to accompany her to one of her Relations, whither ſhe had a Deſign to withdraw. <hi>Grand Champ</hi> did not ſtick to grant her the Crup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of his Horſe, and convoy'd her till ſuch time as that he had put her into a place of ſafety.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Florange</hi> was as impatient to hear of his Wife's Commerce, as if it had been ſome good news he was to receive. Thus ſeeing that ſhe delay'd her Anſwer too long, he ſent her the Fellow he had caus'd to deliver <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Letter to her, to inform her, that ſhe was to make more haſte. This man found her Chamber-door o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; and having ſeen upon the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Letter ſhe had left there, he carry'd it to <hi>Florange,</hi> as thinking it to be the ſame he expected. <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> open'd it haſtily. But what a wonderful amazement, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of what he expected to find
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37055:53"/> therein, he met with a thouſand Reproaches. She accus'd him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things, of having him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf contriv'd the Letter ſhe had receiv'd from <hi>Mainville;</hi> and he could not convict her of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, becauſe he knew not this Marquis his Hand. She alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him whither ſhe was gone, adding, that ſhe would no longer live with a man that us'd her rather like a Tyrant than a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Florange</hi> knew himſelf innocent, and that far from being diſabus'd of his Wife's Intrigue, he every day thought her more cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, yet could he not hear of her Departure without grief. He ſuſpected that ſhe was gone to tax his Carriage, and that having no Proofs to convict her, her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints would prevail in the Minds of her Relations o're thoſe he might make of her ill Conduct.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37055:54"/>
            <p>Thus ſeeing that he had taken his meaſures ill, he did not waver to go ſeek her out, and took Coach in that Deſign with his Wife's. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom he little ſuſpected of being privy to her Concerns: For ſhe was a Goſſip, that under the Oloak of Devotion knew admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly well how to play her Part. He queſtion'd her however on the Road, whether ſhe knew any thing of the matters in agitation; But ſhe affected a falſe Hypocriſy, meaning to perſwade him of the Marchioneſſes Honeſty: and that beſides, ſhe was not a Girl to be concern'd in an Intrigue. When they were Two Leagues from the place they came, a Horſe of his loſt his ſhooes, and they were fore'd to halt, to have him ſhoo'd again. <hi>Florange</hi> was alſo a little ſickiſh, which oblig'd him to go into an Inn to drink a little Wine. While this paſs'd, the Waiting-Gentlewoman, who had alighted
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37055:54"/> out of the Coach, ſaw a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of People flocking together at the end of the Village; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing naturally curious, as all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men commonly are, ſhe went on that waywards, to inquire into the matter. When ſhe was come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe was told a thing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what extraordinary; namely, that a man after having alighted at an Inn, had ſent back his Horſe four Leagues thence, to a perſon of whom he had borrow'd it; that afterwards he had put himſelf to Bed, pretending he was ſick, and had ſent for a Chyrurgeon, who had let him Blood; but that this Chyrurgeon was no ſooner gone, but that he had himſelf unty'd his Arm; and that in ſhort, he had ſhed ſo great a quantity of Blood, that there were no more hopes of his Life.</p>
            <p>The Novelty of the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled this Womans Curioſity; and ſo much the more, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37055:55"/> that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her Lady upon the Crupper of <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Horſe, ſhe had great Suſpicions it might be him all this Diſcourſe was of. Thus ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd herſelf to ſee whether ſhe was not miſtaken, that ſo ſhe might afterwards give the Marchioneſs a faithful account. As ſoon as ſhe had caſt her eyes upon that Wretch, ſhe really knew him to be the wretched <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> who was in a very bad Condition. He on his ſide was not wanting to know her again immediately; and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the People to withdraw, as being to diſcourſe her in private. <hi>I die,</hi> he ſaid to her, <hi>the most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented of all men, ſince that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which hitherto had been againſt me, now favours me with your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, when that I leaſt expected it, to be the Witneſs of my laſt Words. You may tell Madam</hi> de Florange, <hi>that I have my ſelf advanc'd my Death, as after her ſlights not being
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37055:55"/> able to ſurvive. Perhaps that one day ſhe will regret ſo faithful a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Be it as it will, I only wiſh her happineſs.</hi> At theſe Words a Convulſion Fit ſeiz'd him; and the Damſel being willing that he ſhould die in other Hands than hers, call'd for the People again into his Room; and while they were buſy in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating this Unfortunate Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhe made away through the Crowd, without notice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken of what was become of her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Florange</hi>'s fainting Fit had kept all his Servants about him, and hinder'd them from knowing what paſs'd, which their Ladies Woman was not ſorry for, becauſe that it was to be feared, that if <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Adventure had come to his Maſter's knowledg, he would have gone and diſcours'd him, and that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> would have told him all, for the diſcharge of his Conſcience. In fine, after that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37055:56"/> 
               <hi>Florange</hi> had re-collected his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, he took Coach again with her, and they came to the Place of the Marchioneſſes Retreat. <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> made great Complaints to their Kinſman, that his Wife went ſo away without ſaying a word to him: But the Kinſman being prepoſſeſs'd with what the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs had told him in her Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, anſwer'd him, that being of ſuch an Humour, he ought not to marry, ſince there was nothing that madded a Vertuous Woman more, than when her Husband doubted her Vertue. <hi>For my part,</hi> added he, <hi>I ſhall never adviſe her to return with you, at leaſt, unleſs you expreſs a mighty regret for what is paſs'd. Florange</hi> ſeeing himſelf baffled in this manner, would have ſpoke of two Letters he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; but his Kinſman reply'd upon him, that if that was all he had to alledg againſt her, he might be gone as he came, and that all his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37055:56"/> own Relations would eſpouſe the Defence of his Wife. Thus was <hi>Florange</hi> forc'd to ask his Wife's Pardon, though in his Soul he knew that the fault lay not at his door.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> having need of the Protection of this Relation in many things, and particularly in this occaſion, wherein it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to juſtify her Conduct, of which it was impoſſible to hinder Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the World, after what had newly happen'd, did after this eaſily comply with the Counſel he gave her, of coming to a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with her Husband. They ſtaid the reſt of the Day at his Houſe, and all the next; and <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> being gone out for a moment, the Waiting-Gentlewoman took the time of his abſence to entertain her Lady with the ſad Adventure of the Unfortunate <hi>Grand-Champ.</hi> The Marchioneſs could not retain her Tears at ſo piteous a Relation, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37055:57"/> joyning ſome Regrets to the Tears ſhe had ſhed, ſhe told her Woman, that he merited a better Fortune. This Diſcourſe ſurpriz'd that Maid, as knowing how much ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd him as long as he liv'd, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſhe could not hide her amazement from her. But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs interrupting her, accus'd her of having an ill Opinion of her, ſince that after all the Inſtances of Love thar <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> had given her, ſhe could not, at leaſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being the moſt ungrateful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World, hear that any ill was befallen him without being griev'd. <hi>This is a tardy gratitude, Madam,</hi> the Damſel then cry'd, <hi>and you would have oblig'd him much more, if you had ſhewn it while he was well. I have ever had a ſence for him,</hi> reply'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, <hi>but could not then ſhew it without hampering my ſelf in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</hi> Mainville <hi>would have been jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and perhaps that thinking me
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37055:57"/> in love with</hi> Grand-Champ, <hi>he would have ſought out a Conſolation for my inconſtancy, in the choice of an other Miſtreſs. That is to ſay, Madam,</hi> the Damſel anſwer'd, <hi>that you lov'd poor</hi> Grand-Champ, <hi>but did not love him ſo well as</hi> Mainville. <hi>How diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling are Women! I thought you as nice as any perſon living in your Love: Nevertheleſs by what I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, you prefer Number before Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy.</hi> It is very ſeldom known that a Woman dare talk in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to her Lady; but ſee what a Confident may do: and I fancy, that if this Maid had been leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of her Concerns, ſhe would have been more cautious in her words. Be it as it will, Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> imagining ſhe might ſuffer, ſhould ſhe leave her in theſe Sentiments, <hi>You mistake me in what I have ſaid,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>and you groſly confound Love and Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment. There is nevertheleſs a great deal of difference between the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37055:58"/> One and the Other. The Motions of Love are tender and paſſionate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, excited by Sympathy: whereas thoſe of Gratitude are only ordinary Movements, that are wont to ariſe from ſome Benefit that one has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. But, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Damſel, <hi>if thoſe Motions which Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude excites, are ſo common as you ſay, they ought not, methinks, to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the ſhedding of ſo many tears; and yet this is what you do. Tell me, I beſeech you, how this comes to paſs: for I fancy'd, that People affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted themſelves in ſuch manner on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they were lively affected. This you are miſtaken in,</hi> reply'd the Marchioneſs, <hi>as you were but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment agoe, when you confounded Gratitude and Love. A great grief never appears ſo much outwardly as does a mean one: and one would have a bad Opinion of the ſenſibility of a Perſon, that ſhould ſhed tears at the newneſs of a great misfortune. One muſt remain ſeiz'd till that time di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37055:58"/> the ſtrength of the grief, leaves to man his wonted Functions. Then it is that the Eyes diſtill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Water, as a mark of his Affliction. If I do not make my ſelf well underſtood,</hi> added the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>I am going to give thee a very familiar Compariſon: Thou know'ſt that Cold, when it is extream, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes all things, and principally Rivers, whoſe courſe remains conceal'd by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Ice that appears upon the Surface of the Waters. It is even the ſame thing with a great Grief in the Heart of Man. His Tears are ſtopt; and as the Current of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers only appears when the Cold is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh'd, ſo his Eyes only ſhed Tears when the Affliction is no longer ſo ſtrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the Reaſons the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs gave her Woman, to make her apprehend, that ſhe might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail: <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s misfortunes, without loving him. Nevertheleſs, ſhe bid her enquire after him, when
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37055:59"/> that they paſs'd by where ſhe had left him. That ſhe needed only to feign ſome need to alight out of the Coach, and that ſhe might take that time to do what ſhe bid her. The Morning being come, they all ſet forwards on their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and the Damſel having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd her Commiſſion, ſhe was told, that <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> was dead but a moment before. She acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Lady with it when they were arriv'd; and theſe Tidings renew'd her grief.</p>
            <p>During theſe Occurrences, the Marchioneſs had an Affliction which much more affected her than <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Death. <hi>Mainville</hi> remain'd Two Months without writing to her; and ſhe did not doubt after ſuch great marks of his forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but that he had got ſome new Miſtreſs. She daily complain'd to her Woman of her misfortune, and of Mens Inconſtancy. <hi>They are all ungrateful,</hi> ſaid ſhe to her, <hi>and the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37055:59"/> Ladies are fools for loving them. Their flames lact only just ſo long as they find ſatisfaction therein; and as fondneſs only encreaſes by deſires, as ſoon as theſe deſires are fulfill'd, theſe fondneſſes quickly become little or nothing. They never ſee you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, but out of a luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: nay, nor would they ſee you at all, were they not afraid of being tax'd with ill-breeding. I leave thee to judge what a Lady can ſay after this; and if being wonted, as ſhe is, to the Movements of a tender and a paſſionate Love, ſhe reſts ſatisfy'd with theſe Civility-Viſits.</hi> Mainville, <hi>the ungrateful</hi> Mainville, continu'd ſhe, <hi>is not exempt from theſe weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; and thou ſeeſt after all that I have done for him, what his ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>Mainville</hi> paid the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel well for being in his Intereſts, ſhe moſt commonly durſt not take his part, finding her ſelf, that he was mightily to blame in that he did
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37055:60"/> not write to her. However, being unwilling utterly to abandon him, ſhe endeavour'd to give her Lady ſtill ſome hopes, telling her one while, that his Letters might miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, another, that he was ſick, and that otherwiſe ſhe would have heard of him. But the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did not ſuffer her ſelf to be ſo eaſily impos'd on: She knew that a Man of <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Quality ſent a Meſſenger on purpoſe, when Two Poſts had fail'd him; and that let a Man be never ſo ſick, he never forgets his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>About that time Fame, which carries throughout the whole Earth the Actions of Great Men, blaz'd about, that <hi>Mainville</hi> had ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd himſelf above all others in a Battel. At theſe Newes the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, who was as ſenſible to Honour as any Woman in the World, found her tenderneſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive. The Reſentment ſhe had of her Lover's forgetfulneſs, had made
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37055:60"/> her diſcontinue writing to him: She then took Pen and Ink, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to him the ſatisfaction ſhe had in his Heroick Performances. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſhe mingled ſoft and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Reproaches with the Praiſes ſhe beſtow'd upon his fine Actions; inſomuch, that one might ſay, that her Letter was both a Letter of Love and of Civility. <hi>Mainville</hi> was exactly of the Humour of thoſe People the Marchioneſs had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd to her Woman; too eaſy Conqueſts became flat to him, and he had been for ſome time diſguſted becauſe ſhe had done too much for him. But Two Months Abſence making him look upon her then as a New Miſtreſs, he renew'd writing to her in very paſſionate Terms, ſeeking ſorry Excuſes to colour the little Conſideration he had ſhewn for her. The Weakneſs of People in Love, is ſo extraordinary, that the Marchioneſs was ſatisfy'd with his Reaſons, as if they had been
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37055:61"/> good. Thus their Intrigue was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd as before, and all as much charm'd with one another as they had ever been; they let not a Poſt ſlip without interchanging of Letters.</p>
            <p>This Commerce laſted during the reſt of the Campaign; and being ready to end, <hi>Florange</hi> being at <hi>Paris</hi> upon a Law-Suit, and ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting that <hi>Mainville</hi> writ to his Wife, repair'd to his own Home, to hinder him from ſeeing her at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the Army. His Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſomewhat neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <hi>Mainville</hi> was really re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to ſee her on his way. Yet was it in vain: for though <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> knew him to be at home, as he would have been ſorry to have come ſo near to no purpoſe, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd himſelf, as a Miller's Boy, to ſee his Wife. This being done, he mounted upon a Mule, with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sacks under him; and in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipage came to the Court of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37055:61"/> Caſtle one day that he knew him out a hunting.</p>
            <p>He was inform'd, that it was the Marchioneſſes Woman that caus'd the Corn to be meaſur'd before her, and who receiv'd the Meal; ſo as that he fancy'd it would be no hard matter to make himſelf known. But this Nymph little dreaming, that the Marquis <hi>de Mainville</hi> was become a Miller's Boy, began, without look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him much in the Face, to rattle him, for that his Maſter had not the time before reſtor'd all the Meal he ought to deliver: That is to ſay, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that ſhe accus'd him of being a little Thieviſh. <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> laugh'd heartily in himſelf at her miſtake; but referring till an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time to rally her for it, he got up to her to preſs her Hand, thinking, that after that ſhe would no longer take him for a Miller. But the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, far from gueſſing what that meant, call'd him inſolent Raſcal; which made all the People flock a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37055:62"/> him, beginning to threaten him. Then the Damſel viewing him more earneſtly, and perceiving the fault ſhe had committed, ſhe was at a very great loſs how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair it: for now was it a little too late, all People flocking to ſee the Miller. The Marchioneſs acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally return'd from walking, and having enquir'd why all her People ran that waywards, ſhe was told the occaſion, and going that way her ſelf, her ſurpriſe was extream, when ſhe knew <hi>Mainville.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, without making any thing known of her amazement, ſhe ſaid, that he ought to be ſhut up, and that when her Husband was return'd from hunting, he ſhould order what he deem'd fitting for his Puniſhment. Her preſence of Mind was admirable in this occaſion; for ſhe freed him by theſe means out of her Servants Hands, ſome of whom might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have known him.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:37055:62"/>
            <p>Thus was he led into a Tower ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Criminals; but he was no ſooner there, than that the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel came to fetch him thence, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey him to her Ladies Feet. He there forgot the Fright he had been in, when he ſaw himſelf ſurrounded with all <hi>Florange</hi>'s Domeſticks. Theſe Two Lovers upbraided one another tenderly, for having been ſo long without writing to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and Love largely rewarded them for the pains it had made them ſuffer. However, after ſeveral ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes it became <hi>Mainville</hi> to think of being gone; for <hi>Florange</hi> was every moment expected, and it was neceſſary to ſhun his Preſence. The Marchioneſs was the firſt to mind him of it, and he was ſo charm'd with her Preſence, that it was quite out of his thoughts. But conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Dreſs, his getting off was difficult: for a Servant might ſee him go out, and he would not have fail'd of ſtopping him, thinking he
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37055:63"/> did a fine Job. The Marchioneſſes Woman ſeeing their perplexity, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to give him a Suit of her Cloaths, ſaying, that ſince ſhe had done all the miſchief, it was but Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice that ſhe ſhould bring a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <hi>Mainville</hi> willingly receiv'd her Offers; and knowing that he ſhould find his Mule at the Park-Gate, he took leave of his Miſtreſs, after having aſſur'd her of a Love-Proof againſt all things.</p>
            <p>He took his way along a Wood, that reaches from the Park of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi>'s Caſtle, to a ſmall Village, but half a League thence. So far went he without any ill Encounter. But when he was beyond it, he met with <hi>Florange,</hi> who was unhappily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from hunting. The other Hunters had taken through an other way, and <hi>Florange</hi> was all alone, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in meditating on the Pleaſure he had that day taken in hunting, or perchance in thinking on ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe that was not ſo agreeable.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37055:63"/> No ſooner did <hi>Mainville</hi> perceive him, but that he ſought to get out of his way; but <hi>Florange</hi> having by chance caſt his Eyes on that ſide, fancy'd him, by his Garb, to be his Wife's Woman, and in that Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ran full ſpeed to him. As ſoon as he had overtaken him, he ask'd him, whither ſhe was a going: for <hi>Mainville</hi> being mask'd, he ſtill took it to be the ſame Perſon. <hi>Mainville</hi> made him anſwer, that he was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and that not knowing him, ſhe did not think her ſelf oblig'd to give him an account of her actions. <hi>If you do not know me,</hi> then <hi>Florange</hi> reply'd, <hi>you are certainly a Thief, ſince that this Rigging belongs to my Wife's Woman. I took you at firſt for her, but I now perceive that I am miſtaken. I am neither the one nor the other,</hi> Mainville reply'd, <hi>and you are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in the Cloaths as well as in the Perſon. Be advis'd by me, purſue your way, without inſulting me any longer; otherwiſe you may pay for your
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37055:64"/> intruſion. I am content,</hi> reply'd <hi>Florange; but firſt unmask your ſelf, that I may judge by your face, whether I am miſtaken or not. Mainville</hi> was far from doing it; inſomuch, that <hi>Florange,</hi> who never was civil in his Life, ſeeing that he excus'd it, ſet himſelf to ſnatch off his Mask.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi> went not to his Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Expedition without good Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, that in caſe of Accident, he might be in a poſture of defending his Life. Thus ſeeing himſelf preſs'd, he drew out one of them from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Petticoats, which ſtopp'd <hi>Florange</hi>'s Rage: for naturally he had a great reſpect for all ſorts of Fire Arms, running, at leaſt, as faſt in his Retreat, as he had done when he came to accoſt <hi>Mainville.</hi> When he was in the Village I lately menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd, he began then to breathe, and ſounding an Horn, he call'd all his Hunters, that could not be far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. They forthwith rang'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about him, and <hi>Florange</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37055:64"/> related his Adventure to them, exhorted them to run after the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, ſaying, that he muſt needs be a High-way-man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi> hearing the Call, did very much ſuſpect that he was going to be purſu'd; thus being very willing to eſcape further trouble, if he could, he ſpurr'd on. But his Mule not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo faſt as Horſes, the Huntſmen overtook him before he could get to a Wood he thought to have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken himſelf to. They call'd out immediately to him, to yeild him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up; but chuſing rather to dye, than expoſe himſelf to the Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Enemy, he took his Two Piſtols in his Hands, and cry'd out to the firſt that advanc'd, that it ſhould coſt him his Life, if he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to do any Violence to him.</p>
            <p>In this nick of time there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd Officers to come by, that were returning from the Army; and they ſeeing ſo many Men attacque a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:37055:65"/> Woman, they ſided with her, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her, that no hurt ſhould be don her, unleſs they were all firſt kill'd. After they had thus offer'd their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to <hi>Mainville,</hi> they ask'd <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> and all his Company, what that Lady had done to them, that they us'd her with ſo little Civility; And as <hi>Florange</hi> had only ſpoke to them of his Suſpicions, they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd away <hi>Mainville</hi> in ſpight of <hi>Florange,</hi> and promis'd to guard him whither he pleas'd. When he was gone a League from thence, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſaid he to them, <hi>you have taken a great deal of pains, and I hope one day to return the Civility: for though you know not who I am, yet do I know you. In the mean while; if you are minded that the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation I have to you, ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, you will ſuffer me now to go, without having the Curioſity of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who the Perſon is whoſe Defence you have undertaken.</hi> At theſe words they all made him anſwer, out of a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37055:65"/> perſwaſion that he was a Woman, that they would not forſake her till they had brought her to her own Home; and <hi>Mainville</hi> ſeeing their Obſtinacy, unmask'd himſelf, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing them very much in making himſelf known.</p>
            <p>The Command he had in the Army, afforded him a great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Beſides, he was of ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a Family, that many people were bound to have a reſpect for him. Thus theſe Officers ask'd his Pardon for having oblig'd him to make himſelf known againſt his will, as ſuſpecting that he had put himſelf into a Diſguiſe upon ſome occaſion that he was not willing ſhould be known publickly. <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> being a well-bred Gentleman, told them, that after the Service they had done him, it was eaſie for him to excuſe their Curioſity. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that he begg'd of them, not to make the leaſt mention of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, becauſe that there were
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37055:66"/> people who delighted in making the worſt of all things. He embrac'd them all after this; and thus having got himſelf off from this bad Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he went to find out his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who were not far diſtant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Florange,</hi> who was in Deſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, for that theſe Officers had made him miſs of his aim, making reflection of what had newly befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len him, fancy'd there muſt be ſome Myſtery underneath All, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his own Houſe with his Soul full of Suſpicion. At his arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val he ask'd his Wife's Woman, whom ſhe had lent her Cloaths to; and this Queſtion having puzzled her, ſhe bluſh'd, inſomuch that <hi>Florange</hi> having obſerv'd ſome Change in her Countenance, he preſs'd her ſtill more to tell him what ſhe had done with them. She then ſtutter'd, ſaying one while, ſhe had lent no body any Cloaths, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſhe had quite forgot to whom it was. <hi>Florange</hi> judging
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37055:66"/> by her Confuſion, that ſomething had paſs'd which it was not thought fitting he ſhould know of, went di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to his Wife's Chamber; to whom he put an Hundred Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſo he might get from her ſome light into this matter. The Marchioneſs had newly been told what was befallen <hi>Mainville</hi> and her Huſband, and how the former had got out of the other's Hands. Thus having nothing to fear on that ſide, ſhe made him anſwer, that he made a great deal of noiſe for a Garment, or ſo; and that ſhe did not enquire ſo much as he, with what her Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did with her things. During theſe Tranſactions, the Miller of the Houſe arriv'd, and finding all the Doors open, he mounted into the very Chamber where <hi>Florange</hi> was. <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſaid he to him, without firſt enquiring, whether he was in an Humour to hear him, <hi>I come to aſſure you, that it was none of my Lads that was ſawcy to my Ladies
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37055:67"/> Woman: they are all at the Mill; and I neither challenge him nor his Mule, which you may make what Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample you pleaſe of. It is ſome Rogue or other, that ſays he belongs to me, that ſo he may do me an injury; but good my Lord, let me beſeech your Worſhip, to protect me in this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince you have the Knave in your hands, and that you can by the force of torments, draw the Confeſſion of his Crimes from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What this man ſaid, was <hi>Hebrew</hi> to <hi>Florange,</hi> who knew not what paſs'd; but being told the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Miller's Man, he gave order for the fetching him out of Priſon, and that he ſhould be brought to him that very moment. Thoſe that were officious to obey him, ran immediately to the Tower where he had been ſhut up; but they found the Door of it open, and the Bird flown. Thus they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd much amaz'd, to tell <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> that ſome body had let the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37055:67"/> Priſoner eſcape, and that they knew not who it was. At theſe words his Suſpicions re-doubled, ſo much the more as that he then remembred that the Damſel he perceiv'd had a Mule, and that there was great probability of her being the Miller's Man.</p>
            <p>He ſent the Miller away very much ſatisfy'd, by telling him, that he meant him no harm; but ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to dive into this myſtery, he ask'd his Wife, what was become of the Priſoner, and by whoſe order he had been put out of Priſon. <hi>He must needs,</hi> the Marchioneſs reply'd, <hi>have found the Secret of making his Eſcape himſelf, and I know no body here that would have been ſo bold as to have done it without your Orders. The People that have been concern'd in't, Madam, Florange</hi> reparty'd, <hi>are more ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to your Ladyſhips order than to mine; and however you defend your ſelf, yet do I ſmell out your Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:37055:68"/>
            <p>This Converſation was upon the point of being keen on both ſides, when the ſame Relation that had reconcil'd them, came in. <hi>You come very ſeaſonably,</hi> ſaid <hi>Florange</hi> to him, <hi>to do me Juſtice. You accus'd me of being whymſical and jealous; but I do not think you would harbour that Opinion, after what I have to tell you.</hi> He thereupon acquainted him with what had newly happen'd, and did firmly believe, that he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take his part, when the other call'd him Viſionary more than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>You rave Couſin,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>and I am very ſorry I muſt tell you, that you ſerve for a Laughing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock to all our Countrey. I ſhould make a Mock of you as well as the reſt, were I not your Kinſman; but I muſt at length come to that, as no longer finding any means of excuſing you in the World. I am not ſo mad, Couſin,</hi> reply'd <hi>Florange</hi> to him, <hi>as you would fain make me believe: and if the like thing befel you, you would
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37055:68"/> oblige me, in acquainting me what you your ſelf would ſay of it. I ſhould ſay,</hi> his Kinſman reparty'd, <hi>that a real, or a falſe Miller was come to my houſe, and that ſeeing himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd, he had forc'd his Priſon. As to the Habit, which you make the principal Cauſe of your Diſquiets, I would ſtill ſay, that my Wife's Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had lent it to ſome friend; that I had met with this friend on the way; that ſhe would not make her ſelf known, and without tormenting my head, to dive into the reaſon, I would let all people be at quiet at home, which would let me be ſo. That is to ſay,</hi> reply'd <hi>Florange, that you would be a very convenient contented Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. So convenient,</hi> the Couſin anſwer'd, <hi>that I would never think ill of my Wife, unleſs I ſaw it with my own Eyes. Beſides, to what purpoſe,</hi> continued he, <hi>d' ye ſo much ſhrift into a thing which can only afford us matter of trouble? And ſhould I not rather chuſe to live as all well-bred
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:37055:69"/> People do, than live as you do.</hi> Theſe Words vex'd <hi>Florange,</hi> inſomuch, that he was going to ſay ſome diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging things to his Relation, when that this latter, to avoid his ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, went his ways, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leave of him.</p>
            <p>Some days after a Letter came from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Florange,</hi> by which he had notice, that his Law-Suit was ready to come to a Trial, and that his Preſence there was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. I intimated a while agoe, that he had laid aſide the Care of this Law-Suit, to hinder <hi>Mainville</hi> from ſeeing his Wife. His Jealouſie ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then rather augmented than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh'd, he reſolv'd to take her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with him, that he might be the better ſecured of her Conduct. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he was got to Town, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that pretended to be a Friend of his, but meant to banter him, as knowing his Weakneſs, told him, that if he was ſo much concern'd to know whether his Wife was honeſt,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37055:69"/> he would furniſh him with a good contrivance. That he knew a famous Female Fortune-teller, to whom nothing was unknown, and that if he would conſult her, ſhe would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with ſuch things as would ſurprize him. <hi>Florange</hi> did not want Wit, ſo as that knowing out of what motive this man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd him in this manner, he thank'd him coldly for his offers; adding, that it did not belong to all People to concern themſelves in the Affairs of a Husband and Wife. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs <hi>Florange</hi> conſider'd in himſelf of what he had ſaid to him, and being ſilly enough as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that a Fortune teller could convict his Wife of the Intrigue ſhe had with <hi>Mainville,</hi> he enquir'd, under hand, where thoſe ſort of People dwelt, and was not long without being inform'd of the Lodgings of a Woman that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that way. None but Fools went to her Houſe, or Perſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37055:70"/> credulous. Yet not one came thence without being unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd: for it was by Chance, if ſhe ſpoke one Truth among a thouſand Lyes. <hi>Florange</hi> repaired thither one Morning without any Retinue, and deſired this Woman to conceal no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from him, of whatever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence the things were that ſhe ſhould find out, either by his Hand or Phyſiogmony. The Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teller, by his words, gueſſing at his Ingenuity, began with making him pay before-hand; then diſcours'd him with what ſhe was wont to ſay to all thoſe that were ſo ſilly as to come and conſult her. <hi>Florange</hi> knowing then how much he was in the wrong, to hope for any thing in her, told her, that it was Pains and Money thrown away, as to come and ſee her; and as ſhe endeavour'd to ſave her ſelf by a World of ſilly Stories, with which ſhe lur'd the moſt credulous, there came a Man into the Room, habited after a caprici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:37055:70"/> manner, and that would have Bug-bear'd little Children. His Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit was Black, all done with ſtreams of Fire; inſomuch that one would have ſaid, that he had been a Devil that was return'd from Hell, or at leaſt, a Man that had borrow'd the form of one. He had a Mask that repreſented a Face to the Life; but ſo diſmal, that a body trembled to look upon it. This Mask was not made of Paſt-board, as all others are, and you would have taken it for real Fleſh. The reſt of his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billement ſuited exactly with the Mask. He had Buskins on, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Lyon's Skin, a <hi>Groteſque,</hi> repreſenting the Furies, and to his very Shooes one would have ſaid, that they had been the Scales of a Serpent, ſo well had Art imitated Nature. This Counterfeit-Monſter held a Wand in his Hand, with which he ſtruck thrice upon <hi>Florange</hi>'s Head. This poor Marquis needed not this Over-plus of terror, having
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37055:71"/> been ſufficiently frighted at the ſight of the Monſter. He was more dead than alive; inſomuch that he would willingly have given the half of his Eſtate to have been from thence. But his Fright was quite an other thing, when the falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpoke to him in this manner; <hi>Since that thou believ'ſt that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune-teller is not capable of telling thee thy Life, I am come my ſelf to inform thee of all thou would'ſt know: Thy Wife is more diſcreet than thou deſerveſt; and though there be ſome Appearances againſt her, theſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances are leſs ſtrong than truth.</hi> Mainville <hi>is neither in love with her, nor ſhe with him, and thou muſt only accuſe thy own Jealouſie, if any one has been ſo ſpightful as to take a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in allaruming thee. The Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thou haſt receiv'd are forged Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and if thou continueſt to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, a great many more will be paulm'd upon thee. Such as thou ſeeſt me, my Buſineſs is to make the living
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37055:71"/> mad, and I ſhall neither ſpare my Contrivances nor my Pains, to diſturb thy Quiet, unleſs thou avail'ſt thy ſelf of my advice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is hard to ſay which of the two, <hi>Florange,</hi> or the Fortune-teller, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd the moſt amaz'd at theſe words: for ſhe could not apprehend who it was that plaid this part. True indeed, that ſhe was not unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the falſe Devils Habillement, having her ſelf caus'd it to be made, to fright ſuch as were fearful. But ſhe knew not who could take it ſo in the nick, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay ſuch particular things to <hi>Florange.</hi> However to render the Adventure ſtill the more extraordinary, <hi>Mainville,</hi> and the Marchioneſs, being egg'd on by the like Curioſity, came to the ſame place, and finding the Houſe-door open they mounted into the very Fortune tellers Chamber, without meeting with any body to ask them their Buſineſs. The falſe Devil had not ſhut the Door, ſo as that <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37055:72"/> and the Marchioneſs entred therein, not in the leaſt expecting the People they there met withal. <hi>Florange</hi>'s Fright was extream at the ſight of them, imagining, that the Devil had made them come without their conſent. But that of <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> and the Marchioneſs was no leſs, ſeeing <hi>Florange;</hi> for then they thought themſelves loſt without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. He that acted the Magician, or the Devil, as you ſhall pleaſe to call him, ſeem'd quite unhing'd and nonplus'd, remaining for ſome time without ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word. But all on the ſudden rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vering his ſpeech: <hi>Admire my Power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſaid he to <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range: Here are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> two Perſons that occaſion thy Diſquiet, whom I have caus'd to come hither on purpoſe to tell thee what familiarity paſſes between them two: Thou wilt learn their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency from their own Mouths, if thou doſt not put confidence enough in what I have told thee. Florange</hi> fell into a Swoon at theſe words; and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:37055:72"/> the falſe Devil ſeeing him in that Condition, repuls'd <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs with his Wand, telling them they had nothing more to do there. They did not ſtay to be told it twice; and the Marchioneſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with much a-do got again to her Coach, in ſhe ſtept, with a Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror more eaſie to imagine than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Florange</hi> continu'd ſtill ſome time in his Swoon, while that the falſe Devil took the Fortune teller into an other Room, to tell her, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the folly; as well as others, to come and ſee her, he had found that Chamber-door open, wherein he entred. That meeting with no body there, and hearing loud talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the next Room, he had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd, and perceiv'd <hi>Florange</hi>'s Voice. And having perceiv'd at the ſame time upon the Bed, that Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit he had upon his Body, he had put it on, to tell him his Fortune, as being inform'd to every little cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37055:73"/> of his Life. That ſhe had ſeen the ſucceſs of it, and that it was her part now to maintain the Fame ſuch an Adventure was going to gain her in the World.</p>
            <p>The Fortune-teller was very glad that Chance had ſo well ſeconded her Cheats: and all haughty upon this Event, ſhe gave <hi>Florange</hi> a Check when he came to his Senſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for that he would not give Credit to the Wonders of her Art. <hi>Florange</hi> would doubtleſs have ask'd her Pardon, if he had had the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but to ſpeak but one bare word; but he was ſtill ſo much afraid, that all that he could do, was to get to a Hackney-Coach that waited for him at the Door. When he was got in he began to breathe, as thinking that the Devil had not ſo much power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him there. He then promis'd never to ſee, as long as he liv'd, any Fortune-teller: and being got home, he us'd his Wife quite otherwiſe than he had done of a long while, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37055:73"/> that if he ſhould uſe her ill, the Devil would riſe up in her defence, as he had threatned to do.</p>
            <p>After this, <hi>Florange</hi> ſtaid ſtill ſome time at <hi>Paris,</hi> and having met with <hi>Mainville</hi> in a Company, he ſpoke to him as if he had never born him any grudg. Nay, he ask'd him what was the Cauſe they did not ſee one another now; inſomuch, that <hi>Mainville</hi> would have been in a ſtrange <hi>Maze,</hi> had he been ignorant of the Fortune-teller's Adventure. But knowing what paſs'd at her Houſe, and how much <hi>Florange</hi> was of a fearful Humour, he knew to what to attribute his Change.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs were not able to comprehend whom they had the Obligation to of what was fallen out; for no body had ever known any thing of their Concerns, ſave <hi>Grand-Champ</hi> and the Damſel I have
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37055:74"/> mention'd: and they knew very well, that neither of them two had revealed their Secret. For the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs had left her Woman at home; and as for <hi>Grand-Champ,</hi> they could not ſuſpect him, as knowing him long ſince dead. But whoever it was, they were endebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, they look'd upon it as a great piece of Service: for they began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to ſee one another, and that too without <hi>Florange</hi>'s finding fault. <hi>Mainville</hi> was not however wanting to have ſome Pre-caution, when he was with the Marchioneſs, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is nothing ſo eaſie to kindle anew as the Suſpicions of a jealous Perſon.</p>
            <p>Thus they liv'd in ſome ſort of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for a time: But as Prudence is very rare in ſtrong Paſſions, theſe Lovers forgot that <hi>Florange</hi> was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally prone to Jealouſie, and that the leaſt thing was capable of giving him Umbrage. They were ever by one another, not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37055:74"/> a moment without enterchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Words: and when Chance ſeparated them, one might in their Faces read a certain Grief, as made thoſe judge that had the leaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in it, that they were not in ill Terms with one another. <hi>Florange</hi> began alſo to doubt that the falſe Devil had told him a Lye, when he aſſured him, that his Wife was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. <hi>The Devils,</hi> ſaid he in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>are Lyars, and a Man muſt be as ſimple as I to put trust to their Words. Beſides there is ſomething in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I do not apprehend: for their buſineſs being to moleſt Mankind, how comes this, if he be a real Devil, to endeavour to cure me of my ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Thou art abus'd,</hi> Florange, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he, <hi>and like a fool, fallest into the Trap. Are not thy Eyes ſurer than all that can be ſaid to thee? And what haſt thou to do with the teſtimony of an Other, when thou thy ſelf doſt but too clearly ſee thy diſhonour?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:37055:75"/>
            <p>Thus confirming himſelf daily more and more in the Opinion, that he had been impos'd on, he took ſomewhat extraordinary meaſures to ſhrift into <hi>Mainville</hi>'s and his Wife's Intrigue. He pretended not to take any notice of their fondneſſes, but reſolv'd to ſurprize them, when they leaſt expected it, and to put them ſo many Queſtions in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Preſence, that they ſhould be nonplus'd. He knew that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Countenance common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover what lies moſt hid in the Heart: and when one does not find one's Conſcience clear, it is an hard matter to keep one's Judgment. Whereupon he one day ask'd them, when they were in a deep Chat, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there was not a great deal of Pleaſure, in entertaining one's ſelf thus aſide with what one loves, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they muſt needs taſt this happineſs often, ſince it was but a few days ago that they had thus been together alone. It is eaſie to imagine
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37055:75"/> the Confuſion theſe Lovers were under at this Diſcourſe; they were in ſuch a Maze they could not give him one bare word of anſwer. But <hi>Florange</hi> judging by the ſtate they were in, that his Suſpicions were but too well grounded. <hi>To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> renew'd he, <hi>is it for you to uſe fineneſs with me? and am not I ſo clear-ſighted, as to know what I ought to believe of it? You love tenderly one another, and I ſhould have but little regard for both, ſhould I oppoſe ſo fine an Amity.</hi> The coolneſs he affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in uttering theſe Words, did ſo to all intents diſorder <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs, that they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but gaze upon one another, as if they had complemented one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſhould anſwer him firſt. At laſt, <hi>Mainville</hi> being confus'd to the higheſt degree, endeavour'd to undeceive <hi>Florange,</hi> endeavouring to perſwade him, that being ſo much his Friend, as he was, he could not, without an extream ingratitude, caſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37055:76"/> his Eyes upon his Wife. <hi>Let's leave our friendſhip there,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> coldly, <hi>and I ſhould be very much too blame, were I contented with your Reaſons, ſince, All dear as I am to you, as you ſay, my Wife muſt needs he dearer to you than I am. She has Charms for Men which I have not, and made as ſhe is, ſhe would have reaſon eo complain, if under the Pretext of our Acquaintance, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to love her. And indeed, you cannot put it out of my head, but that you do her Juſtice. Mainville</hi> being no longer able to endure a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation that madded him, us'd then his utmoſt efforts to inſinuate into him, that he had never had any thoughts of the Marchioneſs: But <hi>Florange</hi> turning towards her, <hi>And Madam,</hi> ſaid he to her, <hi>will you be as inſincere as he, and will you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it to my face, that you have been able to be ſo long expos'd to the Cajol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries of a well-bred man, without ſuffering your ſelf to be affected.</hi> The
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:37055:76"/> Marchioneſs made him anſwer, that he did her the higheſt injury, to put ſuch a Queſtion to her: That her Duty did ſufficiently inform her, that ſhe ought to love him only, and that he ought not to doubt but that ſhe did all that her Duty directed her. <hi>A meer Reſvery, Madam,</hi> he reply'd to her, <hi>is that ſame Duty with which your Ladyſhip pretends to entertain me; and a thouſand Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that are no leſs honest than your Ladyſhip, tread it daily under foot; But ſince you aſſure me, that it is ſtrong enough, as to hinder you from paying to my Lord of</hi> Mainville<hi>'s me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit what you owe it, and that on the other ſide he vows, that the friendſhip he has for me, hinders him from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you what he owes you, you will both do well never to ſee one another more. And indeed, it would be lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Reputation too much at stake, Madam,</hi> added he, <hi>any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſuffer the Viſits of a Man that has not the ſence to know your worth.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:37055:77"/> And you, my Lord,</hi> ſaid he, addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Speech to <hi>Mainville, you would do me a kindneſs, never to ſet foot more in my houſe: for I eſteem my Wife, and do not love people that ſlight her ſo much, or are ſo inſenſible, that thus they can reſiſt ſo many Charms.</hi> At the ſame time he ſcrap'd <hi>Mainville</hi> a long Leg, as much as to ſay, that it was time for him to be gone, and ſhewing him the Door, he made him apprehend thereby, that he was not of a Humour ſo eaſily to be paulm'd upon in his Beleif.</p>
            <p>I ſhall in no wiſe go about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to you in this place, neither <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Amazement, nor the Marchioneſſe's Confuſion. They could hardly imagine what they heard; but however loth they were to obey <hi>Florange</hi>'s Command, they muſt ſubmit; nay, and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. When <hi>Mainville</hi> was gone, the Marchioneſs ſtomacking what had newly happen'd, and being unable to bear with a ſeparation from her
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:37055:77"/> Lover, ſhe began to diſcharge her Anger upon her Husband. She told him, that his Capriciouſneſs was beyond Example, and that ſhe needed only to blaze about his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, to put him out of repute with all the World. <hi>Florange</hi> could have anſwer'd her, that as he had been out of repute a long while, he had nothing more to manage upon that Point, but continuing in the ſame manner he began, he made her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, with a mighty ſerious look, that he perceiv'd the ingratitude of Women; that he had newly done her a great piece of Service, in rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her of a Man that was good for nothing; and that nevertheleſs, inſtead of thanking him for it, ſhe loaded him with Reproaches.</p>
            <p>After this, the Lady could not expect to ſee <hi>Mainville</hi> again at her own Houſe; inſomuch, that when they were minded to ſpeak with one another, they were oblig'd to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Houſe of ſome ſhe friend.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37055:78"/> Theſe Pre-cautions render'd their Interviews much ſeldomer, and by Conſequence much more agreeable, becauſe that Difficulty is wont to be a ſeaſoning to Pleaſures, though that all People are not pleas'd with ſuch a Ragoo. It was then a little after <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> a time that Merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Feaſtings begin at <hi>Paris,</hi> when a Friend of <hi>Florange</hi>'s having been preſented with a Noſegay at a Ball, made him agree, that he ſhould entertain his Lady with the Fiddles. The Lady being inform'd of it, ſent notice to <hi>Mainville,</hi> that he ſhould not let that Occaſion ſlip, without making advantage on't; inſomuch, that he diſguis'd himſelf, that he might not be known in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. It was numerous and fine; and as the Marchioneſs was weary of dancing, ſhe plac'd her ſelf in a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, whither <hi>Mainville</hi> repair'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to entertain her. He would have ſtaid at her Feet till the Ball had been ended, if a Lady had
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:37055:78"/> not come to take him out to dance with her. He could not but out of Civility give her his Hand: But while he danc'd, another Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rader took his Place, and began to ſay ſuch particular things to Madam <hi>de Florange,</hi> that ſhe was mightily ſurpriz'd at it. His Garb was that of a <hi>Gypſey,</hi> which had help'd him much to the accoſting of her. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaid he to her, <hi>Ladies are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly curious, and the Habit I wear, informs you, that telling of Fortunes is my Province. If you doubt it, you need only to give me your Hand, and you will preſently perceive that I am no Bungler in my Profeſſion.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he gave her an Account of <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Amour, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the very end, and when it came to the place of the Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teller: <hi>It is to me, Madam,</hi> added he, <hi>that you have the obligation of being freed from that ill ſtep. I had ſome Relation to that Woman, which oblig'd me to go often to her houſe, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:37055:79"/> I came thither pretty ſeaſonably to do you Service.</hi> After he had given her this Account, he left her, without being to be perſwaded to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf known, though ſhe preſs'd him very much. But as he was going his ways, <hi>Florange,</hi> who had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd his Converſation with his Wife, and who took him for <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> by reaſon he had ſomething of his Air, and of his Shape, ſtopp'd him by the Arm, juſt when he was at the bottom of the Stair-caſe, and told him, that he had ſomething to ſay to him. The Maſque ſtaid at theſe Words, and <hi>Florange</hi> ſeeing that he was juſt ready to hear him. <hi>I thought,</hi> ſaid he to him, <hi>that after having admoniſh'd thee, never to ſee my Wife more, thou would'ſt never have had the audaciouſneſs to diſcourſe her, and particularly in my ſight. But by what I perceive, thou mak'st no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what is ſaid to thee, ſince to the prejudice of my Prohibition, thou haſt been newly talking to her. Now
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:37055:79"/> for once and all, either let this not happen again, or I ſhall uſe ſuch means as ſhall make you repent you did not take my Advice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Maſque, that did not expect ſuch a Complement, was very much ſurpriz'd at it; but having Reaſons not to anſwer ſo keenly as he was talk'd to: <hi>I know not,</hi> he reply'd, <hi>what you mean by this Diſcourſe, and you certainly take me for an other, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never ſpoke with your Lady before to day. Wherefore you could not give me Inſtances of your jealouſie, as you tell me. But ſince I now know that makes you uneaſie, I aſſure you, that for fear of diſturbing your repoſe, I ſhall care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully avoid meeting her, being very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereby to let you ſee, that I ſhall ever Court the Occaſions of obliging you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing could be more hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome than this Anſwer. But <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> being of a Character to be fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, when one crept before him, it augmented his Audaciouſneſs; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:37055:80"/> that ſpeaking a Language ſtill more arrogant than the former, he told the Maſque, <hi>That Excuſes were but ſlight Reparations, when the Offences were real. That thus he meant to chaſtiſe him for his impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as he deſerved.</hi> And at the ſame time laying his Hand to his Sword, he oblig'd the Maſque, in his own Defence, to take one his Foot-man carry'd for him. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance <hi>Florange</hi> would then have been glad he had not begun the Quarrel; but ſeeing that the Maſque did but parry, without making any Thruſt at him, it encourag'd him ſo as to ruſh on upon him, and puſhing blindly on, he ran himſelf upon the other's Sword. However, the Maſque receiv'd at the ſame time a Thruſt quite through the Body, which made him fall ſtone dead on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>The noiſe they had made in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, had made the People run to part them; and <hi>Florange</hi>'s Friends
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:37055:80"/> ſeeing him all cover'd with Blood, and the Maſque lying in the Duſt, ask'd him the Occaſion of their Quarrel. <hi>It is my Wife,</hi> anſwer'd he them, <hi>who is the Occaſion of my Death. Hold me up, I conjure you; for I have but one moment more to live. But if any of you would oblige me, let him go tell her, that in ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my own Blood, I have at leaſt the Comfort of having taken</hi> Mainville<hi>'s Life away.</hi> At theſe Words the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ran immediately through the whole Aſſembly, that <hi>Mainville</hi> was newly kill'd; and this News extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily afflicted the Marchioneſs. She gave deep Sighs, and without minding in that moment either her Husband's Wound, or all that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could ſay of her Conduct, ſhe ran where the Dead Man lay, to ſee if her misfortune was without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. As ſoon as ſhe had caſt her Eyes upon his Cloaths, ſhe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiv'd they had given her a ſalſe Allarum; and ſtudying to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:37055:81"/> what ſhe had newly done, ſhe went to <hi>Florange,</hi> and made his Friends believe, that the Tears ſhe ſhed were only on his account.</p>
            <p>However, ſhe gave her Woman Order, under hand, to enquire who the Dead Man was; and this Damſel being curious enough of her ſelf, reſolv'd to uſe her utmoſt Care. But this needed no great trouble; for as ſoon as the Deceaſed's Mask was taken off, all the Servants of the Houſe knew it to be <hi>Grand Champ;</hi> and ſhe her ſelf going near the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, quickly perceiv'd that they were in the right. For ſome time ſhe could hardly believe what ſhe ſaw, as being pre-poſſeſs'd with his Death, upon the Account that had been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her her ſelf in the Village before mention'd: But you muſt know, that ſhe had been miſinform'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe at the time they imagin'd he had breath'd his laſt, he was only fallen into a <hi>Lethargy,</hi> occaſion'd by the loſs of Blood, and which
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:37055:81"/> he recover'd from ſome Hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>As the Marchioneſs had been well pleas'd to hear of <hi>Grand-Champ</hi>'s Death, inſtead of that of <hi>Mainville,</hi> it put her Huſband into an incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Deſpondency. For beſides the Grief he had to know his Wife's Lover ſtill in a Condition of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing his Reſt, he was out of Countenance for having wrongfully ſhewn his Jealouſie in ſuch good Company: and what is more, he was not without Regret for having kill'd the unfortunate <hi>Grand-Champ.</hi> But what diſquieted him more than all this, is, that the Chyrurgeons durſt not aſcertain he would eſcape from his Wound, as finding it very dangerous. While he lay a curing his Friends us'd their Intereſt to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Pardon; and <hi>Grand Champ,</hi> having no body to revenge his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, they eaſily effected their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. After this <hi>Florange</hi> recover'd by little and little, and ſeeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:37055:82"/> in perfect Health, he us'd his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour to bring his Cauſe to a Trial, that ſo he might return into the Countrey, where he fancy'd he ſhould live more at quiet than at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was in hopes of having it brought to Trial, the Defendants, who had not over good Right, and who found an Advantage of defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Verdict, bethought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of preſenting a Requeſt to the Council, by which they required to have the Cauſe left to an other Parliament than that of <hi>Paris,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that <hi>Florange</hi> and his Wife had therein a World of Relations upon the Bench. The Affair being examined in full Council, <hi>Florange</hi>'s Parties obtain'd what they demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and were referred to <hi>Rouen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Decree was extream cruel to <hi>Mainville</hi> and the Marchioneſs, who notwithſtanding <hi>Florange</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions and Pre-cautions, did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs continue to ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:37055:82"/> They knew <hi>Paris</hi> to be the only place where Intrigues could be conceal'd, and that in the other Towns, however great they might be, one remains expos'd to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all People; a Man of Quality eſpecially not being able to take a ſtep without furniſhing matter for talk. Nevertheleſs having in their Interviews found Pleaſures they could neither of them renounce, without doing a great Violence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves, they contriv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they parted, how to ſee one another at <hi>Rouen;</hi> and no ſooner was <hi>Florange</hi> there, but <hi>Mainville</hi> came thither <hi>incognito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A little before, he had, with his Credit, ſerv'd a Preſident of that Parliament, who had had a great Concern at Court; inſomuch, that not doubting of his Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he went and alighted at his Houſe. There, without ſcruple, he declared to him what brought him to <hi>Rouen,</hi> and that he had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:37055:83"/> for his Service. A thouſand Perſons in this Preſident's Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, would have put on their Gravity, and have likewiſe told him without ſcruple, that he might ſeek out an other Confident; but this Preſident being very willing to make Returns for the Obligation he had to him, and beſides, being no Enemy to Nature, he made him anſwer, that he might diſpoſe of him, of his Houſe, and of all he had in his power. <hi>I'le not have ſo much,</hi> ſaid <hi>Mainville</hi> to him; <hi>and all I require of you, is to lend me one of your Coaches, when I go abroad with a Parliament-Robes. For when I go to my Mictreſſes Houſe, I mean to be taken for you; and all that we are to have a care of, is, that it be not known that I am here. Thus you muſt make me paſs in your own Houſe, for one of your own Relations; and if People wonder that I make no Viſits in the Town, you may ſay, that I am ſick. If this was the only thing to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy'd,</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:37055:83"/> anſwer'd the Preſident, <hi>the thing would be very eaſie. I know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, without your needing to ſpeak to me of it, that you have People here in whom you confide; and I may ſay the ſame thing of mine, whom I need only to forbid ſpeaking, that you were at my Houſe, to bind them to ſilence. But the Difficulty that I find herein is, that you would, methinks, pay a Viſit to the Marchioneſs under my Name, and that when you are at her Houſe, it ſhould be thought to be me. Right,</hi> Mainville reparty'd, <hi>And this is juſt what I deſire: And if I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Publick, I will take my time ſo well, as never to go to her Lodgings but when her Husband is abroad. I agree to't,</hi> the Preſident anſwer'd; <hi>but you are going to ſet me at odds with my Wife. She is jealous to the utmoſt extremity; and as ſoon as ſhe ſhall be perſwaded, like others, that I viſit Madam</hi> de Florange, <hi>I am very much afraid I ſhall have little quiet at home. Let's lodg our Secret with
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:37055:84"/> her,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Mainville</hi> then: <hi>'Tis the means of being all our Safeties. I have thought of that,</hi> reply'd the Preſident; <hi>but two things hinder'd me, one is, that ſhe can only conceal what ſhe does not know; the other, that it would not be handſome for me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage her in this Intrigue. Thus it is much better to undergo her Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi> ſhew'd himſelf Civil, by expreſſing, that he would not purchaſe his own Content at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of his Friend's. But the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident made him anſwer. That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could afford him more Joy, than the doing of him Service; and though he had ſpoke to him of his Wife's Humour, it was not to excuſe himſelf from the Buſineſs, but to take their meaſures ſo well, that they might keep their Concerns ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. A Lover is eaſie to perſwade, when it tends to his ſatisfaction. Thus <hi>Mainville</hi> making but mean efforts to combate the Preſident's
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:37055:84"/> Civility, conſented to all he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. He then caus'd a Coachman and two Lacqueys, to be dreſt up in the Preſident's Colours; and when he went abroad, not a Perſon, but took him for the Preſident, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Diſguiſe. And indeed, all People ſaluted him in the Streets, principally thoſe that had any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, pretending he would have ſome regard to their Civility, when he ſhould come to try it. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, for the better deceiving of them, he took care to conceal his Face with his Handkerchief, ſo as that not any perſon living took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Cheat; ſo much the more, as that he never went to the Marchioneſſes Houſe, ſave when her Huſband was gone to ſolicite his Judges, which ſhe fail'd not of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him immediate notice of, that ſo they might not loſe the occaſion of ſeeing one another.</p>
            <p>This he ſped in for five or ſix times, without Fortune's playing
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:37055:85"/> him any ill Prank; but <hi>Florange</hi>'s Parties being allarum'd at theſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Viſits, deſired the Preſident thereupon, to decline being of their Judges, giving him to underſtand, that viſiting Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> ſo often as he did, he could not aſſiſt at the Tryal of their Suit, without giving them a great Suſpicion. The Preſident could eaſily have unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them if he would, but that not being to be done, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Friend's Secret, he ſought out ſorry Excuſes for the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits thoſe Parties fancy'd he made to the Marchioneſs. Thus he reply'd upon them, that they were very much in the wrong, in ſuſpecting him of any partiality: That the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Woman did not render him the leſs honeſt man: That every Individual had his Conſcience to keep: That it was not a ſufficient Reaſon againſt his being a Judge at their Trial: and that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he was reſolv'd to be on the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:37055:85"/> Bench, to ſhew how wrongfully they were allarum'd. He thought thereby to ſerve <hi>Mainville,</hi> who had deſired him to embrace <hi>Florange</hi>'s Intereſts as his own. But theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thinking themſelves loſt without Remedy, after this Declaration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd to blaze about, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Preſident's and Marchioneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Intrigue, as to oblige him to be the firſt to draw off himſelf. They had heard ſince they were in the Town, that the Preſidents Wife was extreamly jealous, and that upon the leaſt appearance of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Infidelity, ſhe was wont to make an horrible buſtle. Thus they fancy'd, that they needed only to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate the Preſident's Viſits to her under hand, and that after this the Intrigue he had with the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would quickly be publick.</p>
            <p>Having form'd this Reſolution, they ſignify'd to the Preſident's La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what they were deſirous ſhe ſhould know: and this News made
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:37055:86"/> her almoſt mad. She immediately loaded her Huſband with a thouſand Reproaches for this new Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and would needs oblige him to promiſe her never to go more to her Lodgings. <hi>She's a profeſs'd Goſſip,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>and your frequenting of her Company is only to abuſe me.</hi> The Preſident was at a very great loſs how to quiet this Woman, whom he knew hard to be govern'd upon that Article. He endeavour'd to perſwade her, that he ſaw Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> only out of reſpect; and that if her Concerns had not been recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to him by all her Friends, he would pay her no more Viſits. But his Lady falling into a Rage, and ſo much the more, as that he would not promiſe her to ſee her no more, ſhe reſolv'd to manifeſt her Jealouſie in ſuch manner, as that Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to forbid him her Houſe.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:37055:86"/>
            <p>While that the Preſident's Lady was thus preparing to diſturb theſe Lovers Repoſe, Fortune, that had ſpar'd them ſince they had been at <hi>Rouen,</hi> contriv'd to play them a Prank, which they had all the trouble imaginable to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from. One Day that <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> had choſen to ſee his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, he was taken with an Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Way, that oblig'd him to return home ſooner than he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. He found the Preſident's Coach at his Door, and was migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pleas'd with the Honour he did him of coming to ſee his Wife, as judging thence he would do his beſt for him, when his Cauſe came to a Trial. Wherefore he muſt needs pay him his Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: But at his entrance into the Marchioneſſes Chamber, he was much ſurpriz'd to find a man before her upon his Knees. The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs ſeeing him come in, was ſtill more ſurpriz'd than he: for it was
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:37055:87"/> 
               <hi>Mainville,</hi> who in the Preſident's Robes, made her a thouſand amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Proteſtations. <hi>Florange</hi> had luckily made a ſtop one moment, to conſider upon the manner of his Behaviour in ſo extraordinary an occaſion. The Marchioneſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd that ſmall time to great advantage: For judging that <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> could not have ſeen <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> his Back being towards him. <hi>Ah, my Lord,</hi> ſaid ſhe to her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>all my Remedies are uſeleſs, and you'l cover me all with Blood, unleſs you put your Handkerchief before your Noſe. Mainville,</hi> who had an infinite ſtock of Wit, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by theſe Words, that <hi>Florange</hi> muſt needs be behind him, and ſeconding the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſſes Artifice, he took an Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief out of her Hands, with which ſhe had rubb'd her ſelf, and which luckily for them, was all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Blood, as having her ſelf bled at the Noſe but a moment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:37055:87"/> Then <hi>Mainville</hi> cover'd his Face with it; and <hi>Florange</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in this Condition, was not ſorry that he was ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as thinking he had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably allarum'd. Thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of quarrelling him, as he had reſolv'd to do a moment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he made him a Complement upon his feigned Indiſpoſition, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Wife ſend for a clean Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief, and fair Water, to waſh his Face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville</hi> was in ſome ſort of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, through the Marchioneſſes Artifice: but ſeeing that <hi>Florange</hi> was ſo very officious to ſerve him againſt his Will, he knew not yet how he ſhould get off from this Affair, when Fortune freed him by a Circumſtance that in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood ſhould have ruin'd him. The Preſident's Lady paſs'd through the Street, and ſeeing her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Coach at the Marchioneſs <hi>de Florange</hi>'s Door, ſhe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:37055:88"/> reſolv'd to go in, her Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie inſpiring her with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand extravagant things. Madam <hi>de Florange</hi> knew her not; but ſeeing an handſome Woman come into her Room, and who ſeem'd a Perſon of Quality, ſhe went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, to pay her her Civilities. The Preſident's Lady ſtept back, with a ſcornful look, and then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her Tongue; <hi>You ought, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, to be ſatisfy'd,</hi> ſaid ſhe to her, <hi>with careſſing my Husband, without loading me with your fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. The Traitor is oftner with you than with me; and I deſign henceforward to ſend all thoſe that have to do with him, to your Houſe.</hi> After this, ſhe fell to loading <hi>Mainville</hi> with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Reproaches, taking him for her Huſband, as being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by his Garb and Wigg, that was of the Preſident's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</p>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:37055:88"/>
            <p>However, <hi>Mainville</hi> ſaid not one word; which made the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the more believe it to be the Preſident, and that finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf culpable, he durſt ſay nothing in his own excuſe. Thus his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence was a new Crime for him: She continued upon the ſame Tone; and after ſhe had pretty well diſcharg'd her Choler, ſhe took him by the Gown; ſaying, ſhe would rather ſtay there as long as ſhe liv'd, than go away without him. <hi>Mainville,</hi> who would willingly have given all things to have been away from thence, made uſe of this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be gone; and being entred with her into his Coach, he on the way, underwent all that a Woman can ſay that thinks her ſelf ſlighted. <hi>Thou doſt well to hide thy ſelf, thou Cheat,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him: <hi>But that Handkerchief thou hold'st before thy face, does not hide from me the Motions of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:37055:89"/> thy Heart. I know whom thou ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſeſt thy Vows to; and all the Careſſes thou ſometimes makeſt me, are only for the better deceiving me.</hi> In ſaying this, ſhe ſnatch'd his Handkerchief from off his Noſe: But her Surprize paſs'd beyond all that I can ſay, when inſtead of her Huſband ſhe ſaw a man ſhe did not know. For out of certain Conſiderations, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident had not let her ſee <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> though he ſtaid in his Houſe; and when ſhe had ask'd him the Reaſon of it, he had ſtopp'd her mouth, by telling her, that there were certain things which Women ought not to know. In the mean while, <hi>Mainville</hi>'s Diſorder was no leſs in this Occaſion, than that of the Preſident's Ladies; but being ſooner recollected, <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid he to her, <hi>I know that this Adventure ſurprizes you: I beſeecb you not to let it be known, and you will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in oblige a Man of Quality, who
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:37055:89"/> is my Lord, your Husband's friend, and a peculiar Servant of all that regards him. I would now tell your Ladyſhip,</hi> continued he, <hi>what has induc'd me to diſguiſe my ſelf as I am; but it is better that you be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of all from his own Mouth, becauſe, that not having the Honour to be known by you, all would be ſuſpicious I might ſay to your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean while, the Coach jogg'd on, and they at length got home, without any other illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than this. The Preſident was then in the Court of his Houſe. He was ſtrangely amaz'd to ſee <hi>Mainville</hi> with his Wife; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up to them, to know how this came to paſs, he was ſtill in a greater maze, when <hi>Mainville</hi> had told him aſide, all that had befallen him. <hi>This is a bad Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,</hi> ſaid the Preſident to him; <hi>and knowing my Wife's Humour, ſhe cannot fail of blabbing it abroad.</hi>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:37055:90"/> However, to top upon her, he told her, that <hi>Mainville</hi> was a man of Quality, who was hamper'd in great troubles; and that it imported his Life, that People ſhould not know of his being in Town: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he beſought her not to ſay the leaſt of it to any Body: and that this was the Reaſon that had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd him to give him a Retreat at his Houſe, without telling her of it. <hi>You think me but an ill Keeper of Secrets, Sir,</hi> ſaid his Wife to him, as already ſuſpecting the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; <hi>and all People have not ſo bad an Opinion of Women as you, ſince that this Gentleman himſelf does not conceal himſelf from Madam</hi> de Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range. <hi>Madam</hi> de Florange, the Preſident reply'd to her, <hi>is a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his, and partakes in all that can befall him; inſomuch, that ſhe will be cautious of diſcovering where he is.</hi> The Preſident's Lady, who was as malicious as any body li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and who had plainly obſerv'd
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:37055:90"/> how <hi>Mainville</hi> had hid himſelf from the Husband. <hi>I believe,</hi> ſhe anſwer'd the Preſident, <hi>that this Lady has ſtill more Intereſt than you ſay, in keeping your Friend's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns ſecret; but I very much doubt whether the Marquis</hi> de Florange <hi>has the ſame Regards for him.</hi> At theſe Words ſhe left them both there; and the Preſident knowing the ſpightfulneſs of his Wife, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd <hi>Mainville</hi> to leave the Town, for fear her Twattle being told a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to <hi>Florange,</hi> he might ſuſpect the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mainville,</hi> notwithſtanding the Pleaſure he took in ſeeing his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, follow'd his Friends Advice, and departed <hi>Rouen.</hi> The Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign began ſhortly after, which ſolac'd him for this Adventure, as finding in the Employs of War wherewith to make him forget for a while the Secrets of Love.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:96"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37055:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37055:97"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37055:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37055:98"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37055:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37055:99"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37055:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37055:100"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37055:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37055:101"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37055:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37055:102"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37055:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37055:103"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37055:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37055:104"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37055:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37055:105"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37055:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37055:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37055:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37055:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37055:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37055:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37055:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:37055:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37055:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37055:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37055:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37055:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37055:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:37055:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:37055:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37055:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:37055:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37055:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37055:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37055:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37055:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:37055:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37055:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37055:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37055:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37055:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37055:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37055:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37055:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37055:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37055:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37055:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37055:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37055:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37055:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37055:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37055:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37055:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37055:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:37055:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37055:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37055:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37055:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37055:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:37055:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37055:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37055:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37055:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37055:130"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:37055:130"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:37055:131"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37055:131"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:37055:132"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:37055:132"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:37055:133"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:37055:133"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:37055:134"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:37055:134"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37055:135"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:37055:135"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:37055:136"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:37055:136"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:37055:137"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:37055:137"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:37055:138"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:37055:138"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:37055:139"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:37055:139"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:37055:140"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:37055:140"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:37055:141"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:37055:141"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:37055:142"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:37055:142"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:37055:143"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:37055:143"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37055:144"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:37055:144"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:37055:145"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:37055:145"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:37055:146"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:37055:146"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:37055:147"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:37055:147"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:37055:148"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:37055:148"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:37055:149"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:37055:149"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:37055:150"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:37055:150"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:37055:151"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:37055:151"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:37055:152"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:37055:152"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:37055:153"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:37055:153"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:37055:154"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:37055:154"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:37055:155"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:37055:155"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:37055:156"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:37055:156"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:37055:157"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:37055:157"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:37055:158"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:37055:158"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:37055:159"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:37055:159"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:37055:160"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:37055:160"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:37055:161"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:37055:161"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37055:162"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:37055:162"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:37055:163"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:37055:163"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:37055:164"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:37055:164"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:37055:165"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:37055:165"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:37055:166"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:37055:166"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="140" facs="tcp:37055:167"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:37055:167"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:37055:168"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:37055:168"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:37055:169"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:37055:169"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:37055:170"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:37055:170"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:37055:171"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:37055:171"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:37055:172"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:37055:172"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:37055:173"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:37055:173"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:37055:174"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:37055:174"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:37055:175"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:37055:175"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:37055:176"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:37055:176"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:37055:177"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:37055:177"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:37055:178"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:37055:178"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:37055:179"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:37055:179"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:37055:180"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:37055:180"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
